Hey, humans, thanks for joining my podcast.
This podcast is a place to share unedited lived experiences regarding mental health.
We'll touch on how it shows up in our lives and provide
some tips that have worked for me and others on how to manage it.
There will be strong language, and definitely the
potential for disturbing and or triggering content.
Please be aware of this and mindful of
others who may be in earshot.
Most importantly, and as horribly fucking
cliche as this sounds, you really do not have to go through this alone.
And hopefully you'll see this and feel this more and more as you listen.
And hey, if this podcast isn't for you, that's fine.
There are lots of them out there.
Find one that speaks to you and helps you.
So, let's talk mental health.
And now the boiler plate and cover your ass claws
On this podcast, unless explicitly stated,
no one on this show is a medical professional in
any way, and as such, no content on
this show is intended to be, whether implied or otherwise,
to be taken as medical advice.
If you are in crisis, please call 988
or 911 or go to your nearest emergency room.
For my fellow LGBTQ plus
community, you can text start to 678678
to reach the amazing people over at the Trevor Project.
Or you can call them at 866-488-7386
or you can even live chat with them on their website at chat
org.
Concertos of chos is sponsored
by self- magnitude, an ethical microrobusiness helping
people show up as their boldest, truest selves at
work, at play, and everywhere in between.
Founded by Maggie Green, a queer, neurodivergent
brand and style strategist, self-magnitude
offers trauma-informed, affirming support for personal brand and style that reflects all of who you are.
Learn more at selfagnitude.com.
And while you're there, check out Maggie's Gay It Forward initiative to support Queer Folks in Need.
How many of you are anxious,
distressed, worrying about the world?
What's happening
I'd say a lot.
There's a lot happening.
You see it on the news, social media, it's everywhere.
You can you can you can't avoid it.
You cannot avoid it.
We feel dread, the disgust,
sick, confused, enraged, so many words, so many words.
because we're not heading in a good direction.
Concerned about the price of eggs, concerned about gas, concerned about whatever you're concerned about.
it's's heavy, and definitely weighs on our mental health.
There is a fine line between appropriate
concern about what's going on in the world and
clinical anxiety, fine line there.
And sometimes it's hard to figure out
where you stand, which side of the line you're on.
When you feel distressed about
things happening in the world, of that's a natural response to a real problem.
But when they start to consume you and
take over, you know, your appetite, your
job, how you interact with people, your relationship.
that could be a
sign that you may be slightly crossing the
line into, you know, clinical, something that might need a different approach to
help you out.
So feeling upset about what's happening
is rational.
It shows that you're paying attention.
It shows at the very least, that you're sympathetic.
you know, you're paying attention, you know what's happening, and it should be piss you off.
And for whatever reason,
self preservation, primal instinct, our brains are wired
to focus on threats, making
the information we are taking in, whether the new social media print, whatever
very, very, very impactful, very impactful.
How do you know when it's too much?
How do you know when it's affecting you the most?
Or in a way that is unhealthy?
Because too much can be unhealthy.
If you are ruminating and it is all you can think about,
it's a problem.
Um avoidance.
If you don't watch the news anymore, if you don't,
you know, stay abreast of what's happening,
you're avoiding everything that reminds you of what's happening.
That could be a problem.
And catastrophizing, you
know, saying things that the world's gonna end, we're all gonna die.
Those are unhealthy.
I know we feel them, and again,
it's okay to feel how you feel, because feelings aren't
always facts, but it's still what you're feeling and it's okay to feel it.
There is a way to worry productively,
and there is a way to not worry productively.
And I think an unproductive
way of worrying is simply ruminating, letting
it control you, letting it make you feel how it's going to make you feel
or allowing it to make you feel how you feel
Productive worrying, I think, would
be getting involved.
You know, you're worried, you're pissed,
So what can you do?
Get involved.
That would be productive worrying.
But how do you do it?
How do you. try to help when all you feel is rage?
All you feel is disappointment, disgust.
What do you do?
When you think about what's happening and
whatever has got you upset, it doesn't have to be what the
convicted rapist is doing today
Are you able to identify
where your concerns are.
So let's have a spectrum, right?
We have a spectrum.
In the middle, we have awareness.
In the very bottom of the scale, we have complete avoidance.
And at the very top of the scale, we have excessive worrying
Where are you all on this scale?
I'm definitely awareness, but also
a little leaning towards the avoidant side
of the scale and not so much the excessive.
But then it fluctuates back and forth.
One day, I'll be like, I don't I don't care, I don't want to see this.
which is what they want you to think.
And then other times I'm excessively
worrying because pretty bad shit's happening.
It's easy for me, but not always, to identify
which part of that spectrum, that scale that I'm on.
and worrying is not inherently bad, but
it's when it starts to consume you and everything
about you, that's a problem.
We got to find a way to deal with that.
Are there changes in your sweep?
Here are things to look for.
Changes in your sweep, changes in your appetite.
Do you sweep too much?
Do you sweep less?
Are you eating?
Are you not eating?
I don't like how the camera's up there, and it looks like I'm staring down here and I'm not paying attention.
So, sweeping, eating, your ability to focus.
Are you able to focus on things that you once cook?
Are you able to focus on the things that you need to be able to focus on,
for instance, surviving, being there for your kids,
being there for your loved ones, being there for you
because you have to show up for yourself
or you can't show up for other people.
For instance, those who
have flown or have seen TV shows or movies where people
are flying and sudden wasak cabin pressure and
the oxygen masks drop down, they tell you, put yours on first
and then help someone who may need it next to you.
Because if you can't help yourself first in this situation,
you pass out, you're unconscious.
You can't help somebody if you're not animated, right?
So you need to show up for yourself.
How do you show up for yourself?
It's a good question.
I'm still trying to figure that out.
I think being
aware, being present in the moment,
being mindful, is how you show up for yourself.
If you are in the moment and you are fully aware
and you are paying attention to what's happening, that's being mindful.
Sometimes being mindful can be painful, but we don't avoid it.
We still have to do it.
We need to be mindful.
I think if more people were mindful in the moment,
I think I've used this word the most in this episode.
If we're mindful in that moment, then we
can understand, or at least try to, of what's happening.
You can't be rational, you can't have sharp thoughts
if you're anxious, if you're upset, if
you're enraged, you cannot think properly.
The brain just kind of.
It's like, no, I'm pissed, I'm going to focus on this.
I don't want to focus on, well, let's see it from their point of view.
Let's
It's hard.
I know.
I know!
I live it.
I know.
But what are some small things we might be able to do to kind of
counteract it, make it a productive worry?
What are some things that you can do this week
today, tomorrow, that can help address what you're concerned about?
I feel this in my core, what most people are feeling.
You're not alone.
I feel it.
It's enraging.
It keeps me on edge.
It keeps me up at night sometimes.
Like, what are we gonna do for the next four years with this much bullshit?
What are
How do we process it?
What?
How do we focus?
How do we do anything?
A large portion of people despise what's happening in
the world and rightfully so, especially here in the U.S. And
there are two popuations who all
want to be heard and understood and be able
to explain from their point of view why what
they see happening is not going to work,
or be sustainable, or benefit anyone that isn't in a certain class
And then on the other side, we have another large population
of people who love what's
happening in the world and the U.S. And this is their jam.
This is they live
for this.
And you're probably thinking, "Well, those people are wrong.
They're stupid.
They're fucking white tr racist rednecks that have zero
education and can't understand what's actually happening right in front of them because they can't critically think.
I feel it.
I do.
I have thought it, I have thought worse things, actually.
My brain has come up with some pretty horrible things
that have even scared me at times, but they're passing
thoughts, pass passive, they just kind of pop in there, and then they're gone.
Sometimes they stick for 15 years, sometimes they just last for a day.
But they happen, and that's okay.
We can't control what our brain decides to pop into our head.
We cannot control that.
But we can control how we respond to it.
by being mindful.
Being in the moment, it's hard.
I know!
But we have to do it.
So we have these two groups of people.
Ah, this is horrible.
Uh.
No, this is how it should be.
It's okay to feel how you feel.
That's the most important thing.
It is okay to feel how you feel,
because there's a lot of people who feel the same way
and who are struggling like you are.
Back in the day, we all decided
whether society is, what it should be, and we all agreed.
We're going to help each other.
Everyone has a role.
Everyone helps each other.
It takes a village.
and that's what society is.
That's what society was supposed to be.
That story was forced down our throats in school
when in reality, we
We invaded.
We raped, we murdered, we colonized, we enslaved,
we did so many horrible things, and we're still doing it today,
none of which of what a society is supposed to be.
Well, that brings
up the question, well, whose definition of society do we go off of?
Well, again, in the US,
we decide, right?
Well, we're supposed to.
If a large enough group of people, more
than half, right, say they do or do not want
X, okay, then the majority typically gets or doesn't get what they want or don't want.
That's democratic society, right?
But that's not how it works.
If enough people say something and there
is enough money involved, then
shit happens, whether in
our perceived favor or in their perceived
favor, and then that brings up another point, ours, theirs.
the division.
There is a reason we were taught
the phrase, "ogether we stand, divided we fall.
I'm sure you remember that.
What was that in history?
Maybe seventh, eighth grade, I think?
Maybe, maybe.
I don't remember.
But what does it mean?
Together we stand dividedider, we fall.
What does that, what does that mean?
It' It's not. another useless quote that we were taught in school.
This one actually matters.
This one means that if we all stood together
all of us came together.
As one, we could get shit done.
But when we're all divided, and everyone is this
or everyone is that, and then some are this and some are that, then we can be controlled.
Governed.
Why?
Because nobody wants to stand together.
Because too many people don't
want to understand why other people feel the way they do.
Now, I know that's hard because
you might feel like I do.
Well, I know why they feel this way, because they're racist.
They're Nazis.
They hate anyone that's not them.
They hate anyone that's not white.
They hate anyone
that is not like them.
Together, we stand divided, we fall.
If you do not stand for something, you
will fall for anything.
You will be led to do say things
that you don't even realize you're being led to do think and
say, which is what's happening today.
I've discussed a little before about the media and
the 24/7 news cycle, and it's for a reason, right?
We discussed this set up a previous episode.
It is for a reason.
It is the algorithms and social media
are there for a reason.
They were created to amplify
all of the negativity, the misinformation,
all of that bullshit is by design, but
because enough people aren't taught how to think critically
they're oblivious to it.
100%.
There are people who are not oblivious to it, and they just simply don't care.
I call that trash, but I digress.
These algorithms were created for a reason.
Keeping us all divided is for a reason.
This purposefully created unbalanced, rigid
view of reality, and we eat it up.
We eat it up.
Why?
Well, we have a clown running the country, a former
TV star, if you will, who
whose words and actions are telling a lot of people that
they can do and say anything they
want, because, well, if our
asshole in the highest office of the U.S. can do it, then why can't I?
That's a problem.
And by design,
people need to wake the fuck up.
You're being manipulated.
I'm talking to those who support this man.
I just saw a video
of, I think it's Mexicans for Trump
or Latinos for Trump, and they're all singing and praising Trump.
and they don't even realize the man fucking hates them and
would deport every single one of them legal or not, which he's doing if he had the chance.
But they've been so manipulated, their fucking singing and
praising his name divided we fall.
Blacks for Trump.
Black people who support Trump, a
man that is racist as fuck, who would rather see
you dead, but here you are supporting and praising him.
Divided we fall.
I mean,
This 24 hour news cycle, the way we are
fed this information activates this
anxiety and these systems in our body that we're not meant
to be on for 24/7.
You know, it can lead.
No, no, no, no, no.
I'm not saying it can lead to, because we all know it will
lead to anxiety.
It will cause you to be depressed.
It will make you feel helpless.
And guess what?
It's by design.
Why?
Because if everyone is anxious and panicked and on the edge of
fuckery, then your minds can't be sharp and focus on what is actually happening.
And we will buy into most anything we're told
because they know if we're divided, we're going to fall for it.
So the media keeps us in the know,
but only, you know, the parts that they want us to know so
that they can keep us in this state
to be governed.
I want to scream at people, and I'm sure you guys you
all do as well, to just fucking wake up, open your goddamn eyes, stand up for something.
just fucking wake up.
Like, it's not hard.
Our education system sucks.
And this is not a knock on the educators, because
it's not the educator's fault.
It's not's not
their problem.
They didn't create it.
We are churning out fewer and fewer people with
critical thinking skills, or any skills, actually, and again, for a reason.
these educators raise your kids, right?
right?
You put your kids in school from what,
8 to 2, 8 to 3, seven, eight hours a day, Monday through Friday,
kindergarten to 12th grade. teachers are raising your fucking kids.
but you all don't take any issue
to find out what they're teaching your kids.
And then comes up the issue, well, who's to say what
can be taught to my kids and what can't be taught to my kids
Divided, we fall.
We are not the greatest country in the world..
We have never been the greatest country in the world.
We are the richest country in the world
and arguably the most fucked
but we're not the greatest.
All of this quote unqu "greatness that the
U.S has accomplished was at the expense of other people.
Wake the fuck up.
If destroying everything we
touch is greatness, then by
God we are the fucking greatest country, and that's disgusting.
It's disgusting.
The reactions, a lot of the reactions were we have to what's happening.
almost identically mirror grief, right?
We have denial, anger, depression, bargaining, accepted..
The stages of grief, may be reframing how we're feeling
as grief, and think of it as those stages might
help us process it better?
I'm not sure.
I don't like grieving anything.
But
it might help.
It's not not helping me, but it might help someone else.
What morals values, traditions
are most important to keep and adhere to
in fucked up times of change that we live in.
What morals, values, and traditions do we hang on to?
Which ones do we keep?
And that brings up a question.
Whose definition of a moral do we go with?
Whose definition of a value?
Whose definition of a tradition?
do we go with?
Well, this is where it falls back to society.
We're all supposed to agree and decide what we believe or don't believe.
But it doesn't work that way.
Who is to say your moral is not
OK, but their moral is who is to say that your
tradition is bad, but theirs isn't?
Why do you go to Mexican restaurants and
eat the delicious food and then immediately leave
and join the Trump bandwagon and want to deport them off.
I cannot make some of this make sense.
And that's one of the most enraging
things is trying to make sense of what the fuck is happening.
You can't, because it doesn't make sense.
It's fucking chaos, chaos doesn't make sense.
The only thing about chaos that makes sense is we know it's fucked up.
Nothing makes sense anymore, and
people are struggling with how to find purpose and hope
in a world that does not make sense.
And we're not even
what, six, seven months into this?
Things were falling apart.
I almost said everything is falling apart, but that's catastroprophizing, and it's not.
A lot of things are falling apart.
And it does seem like a catastrophe, and one could
have argue it is, you know, when human
rights are on the docket and being cut left and right
by a convicted rapist, I mean, first of all,
We put a fucking convicted rapist in the White House.
I don't understand America.
I don't understand the hate.
Now, I understand my hate
for the trash that is causing all of this.
but I don't understand their hate to people who
aren't like them, only because they aren't like them, right?
I hate these people because they're doing horrible things.
They only hate us because we're not one of them.
I might be able to swallow it a little easier
if they actually had a constructive thought on
why they don't like the people who aren't like them.
But they don't.
These are the same people that say, where was Obama during 9/11?
Why was he out playing golf?
He wasn't even fucking president, but here we are.
These are the people that raiseraise our kids.
These are the people that vote.
These are the people that make decisions that should not be making decisions.isions
What who's to say, who can make a decision and who can't?
I can't even find words
on the level
of rage, disgust, anger, disappointment that I have.
I cannot find the appropriate words for it.
What do we do?
How do we survive?
I can tell you till I'm blue in the face.
Be mindful.
Put yourself in their shoes.
Think like them.
in certain situations that doesn't help, nor is it productive.
When something is
negative and it's probably going to stay negative and not change,
There is no point in trying to understand why
there's no point.
You will work yourself up more, trying to understand why somebody thinks the way they do
than if you didn't.
Especially the people we're talking about.
I cannot comprehend the level of
stupid that we are in right now.
I can't.
Like, how?
How?
Money, entertainment, greed
If you're not enraged, you're not paying attention.
If you are paying attention and you're not enraged,
might want to unpack that.
But the people that need to unpack that don't listen to this podcast.
The people that need to unpack that don't because they don't know how.
and or they don't want to to, because they're right, we're wrong.
Yes.
The other side's the same way.
We're right, you're wrong, right?
Who's to say what's right and wrong?
Who's to say what's mor?
Who's to say what's a value?
If you are not hurting someone, I think that's good.
If you are hurting someone, that's bad.
Doesn't get any fucking simpler than that.
Don't be a dick.
Be a good person.
Treat people how you want to be treated.
I can guarantee you these other people don't want to
be treated the way they're treating us, because when we do,
we get all these new nicknames from them.
I understand it is hard not to be a dick.
You know, I'm a huge dick.
I'm not gonna lie.
It's just, I don't know.
My genes
being in tune to what's been going on in the world,
I don't know, but I'm a dick.
And if you come at me with that kind of energy, typically I give it back.
But the tit for tat doesn't get anything accomplished, but sometimes it feels good, right?
It feels good to be enraged and battle with
these people because it makes you feel alive and like you're doing something for a cause
When nine times out of 10, it goes nowhere..
You just get more upset and you deal with the frustration,
because these people are fucking clueless, living in La La Land.
I just don't know how we got here.
I mean, I do.
But metaphorically, I don't.
It's a very gloomy day today.
The sky is gray.
It's raining, just. gently, nice breeze.
I love gloomy days.
But when I'm in a certain mood, they kind of amplify that
mood, and today's one of those days.
I just, I so hard
to comprehend the amount of stupid that exists.
Some people say, "Well, they're uneducated."
A lot of these people have degrees.
PhDs, top of their field, highly educated.
but still believe what they believe.
How do you get so high highly educated and
still keep that closed mind?
How do you do it?
I'm sad for the world.
I'm sad for the people who feel hopeless.
I'm sad.
I'm disgusted
that this is where we are.
You have to stand.
sitting by the sidelines and watching what's happening isn't gonna change anything.
And I know some of you were thinking, even if there was enough enough
of us to try to make a change, it still wouldn't happen because of,
you know, how things are stacked against us.
You know, when the government keeps you crushed and
then penalizes you because you can't take the weight
what the fuck?
But yes, let's keep voting for these people.
Let's keep a weaving what's they feed us and promise
us, how many of you dumb fuckers who probably aren't even listening,
you didn't even know what a goddamn tariff was.
You thought I was the greatest fucking thing in the world.
You all quickly changed your tune when you figured it out.
I'm struggling, y'all.
I am struggling to
find direct direction and purpose and
meaning in this world.
You know, I had music at one time to kind
of escape with and comfort, but the whole fucking
hearing problem ruined that.
I'm not sure what outlet to help get this out.
I don't know.
It would be great if it was violence.
Of course, I'd feel good beating the fucking out of these dumbasses, but that won't accomplish anything.
And then I am sunk to their level, and I refuse
to be seen as that stupid.
I refuse.
So what do we have, just being mindful?
I know.
It's not a lot to go on.
Sometimes being mindful can enhance
the bad feeling, because you're more focused on it.
I know.
I don't have the answers for this.
I don't I don't have the answers.
Everyone is just trying to do what they can to survive and not lose their shit.
Everyone is trying to
understand what's happening and find ways to not let it happen again.
I don't think civilization.
Okay, civilizations, all the ones before
us, don't live long enough to learn from our past.
I mean, look at us.
We have it documented in history.
We know what happened.
Here we are.
I don't have I wish I had more people.
I wish I had more to give you.
We have to stand up for something.
We can't stay divided.
It has gotten us nowhere in the history of this country.
It has gotten us nowhere.
Other people, it's gotten them somewhere.
Same people that have put us where we
are, they get what they want
They retain their power,
and we continuously put them there.
Why?
Why are we so naive and stupid and continue to let this happen?
I'm sad for the world.
Do you know what it's like to feel sad for people you don't know?
It's an odd feeling.
I don't even know how to end this episode.
Just wake up.
Again, I don't think my demographic is
the people that need to wake up listening to this, but I mean, if you are
wake up, you're being lied to.
You're being manipulated.
and if you're okay with that, then you're okay with that.
It's your life to be okay with, right?
If you're okay with that, then you're okay with that.
I just wouldn't think
being told what to do and manipulated is what people want.
Don't give up.
I guess that's what I'll leave you with.
We have gotten through worse, and that's just disgusting to say.
We have gotten through worse, so let's keep going.
We'll get through this.
It's so disgusting.
but it's all I have.
Don't give up.
Keep fighting
unless you're them, then just fucking stop breathing so we all can get on them with our lives.