Hey humans, thanks for joining my podcast.
This podcast is a place to share unedited
lived experiences regarding mental health.
We'll touch on how it shows up in
our lives and provide some tips that have
worked for me and others on how to
manage it.
There will be strong language and definitely the
potential for disturbing and or triggering content.
Please be aware of this and mindful of
others who may be in earshot.
Most importantly, and as horribly fucking cliche as
this sounds, you really do not have to
go through this alone.
And hopefully you'll see this and feel this
more and more as you listen.
And hey, if this podcast isn't for you,
that's fine.
There are lots of them out there.
Find one that speaks to you and helps
you.
So let's talk mental health.
And now the boilerplate and cover your ass
clause.
On this podcast, unless explicitly stated, no one
on this show is a medical professional in
any way.
And as such, no content on this show
is intended to be, whether implied or otherwise,
to be taken as medical advice.
If you are in crisis, please call 988
or 911 or go to your nearest emergency
room for my fellow LGBTQ plus community.
You can text start to 678-678 to
reach the amazing people over at the Trevor
project, or you can call them at 866
-488-7386.
Or you can even live chat with them
on their website at chat.trvr.org.
Concertos of Chaos is sponsored by Self-Magnitude,
an ethical micro-business helping people show up
as their boldest, truest selves at work, at
play, and everywhere in between.
Founded by Maggie Green, a queer neurodivergent brand
and style strategist, Self-Magnitude offers trauma-informed
affirming support for personal brand and style that
reflects all of who you are.
Learn more at selfmagnitude.com.
And while you're there, check out Maggie's Gay
It Forward initiative to support queer folks in
need.
Okay, welcome everybody.
In this first pilot episode, I thought what
better way to start than to share a
bit about myself and my mental health and
that lovely little journey down that witch's road.
There'll be good, there'll be bad, and of
course some really fucked up shit like earlier.
I have been diagnosed with bipolar, autism, ADHD,
CPTSD, borderline personality disorder, and anxiety disorder.
Since January of this year, 2024, as this
is recorded, I developed Meniere's disease and have
lost most of my hearing.
I've been through a lot of shit and
we're going to talk about some of it
today.
Yay!
So I spent many, many years feeling broken,
alone, isolated, like there was something fundamentally wrong
with me that I just could not figure
out.
It seemed that I didn't make friends quite
like other people I knew that made friends.
Theirs seemed to be genuine connections and mine
always kind of felt like a surface level.
I've always had a hard time connecting with
people in most ways that others don't.
And the more I am learning about mental
health and different conditions and traits, the more
I am realizing that I'm not broken.
None of us are.
Our brains are just slightly wired a little
differently than others and some are a touch
fucked.
You know, you can't help it.
The upside of this though, and yeah, there's
an upside to some mental health things, and
one of them is due to the experiences
that I've had at least, it's allowed me
to kind of tune into things and be
more receptive and aware of things that some
people may not be.
Let me give you an example.
Let's say you go to a gathering.
Some people you know, the majority of them
there you know.
There might be some sprinkled in there that
you don't know.
Um, there's food, there's music, there's lots of
noise, there's drinks, adult beverages, non-adult beverages,
you know, there's wine glasses clinking, you've got
ice in a whiskey tumbler clinking around, and
you know, you're just kind of looking around
and taking it in and you know, getting
a feel for the environment.
I don't know about you, but for me,
the first thing I do in strange places
is look for exits and all of the
possible strategies to be able to get out
quickly if need be, whether an emergency or
something with my mental health and I just
need to go.
I don't know if anybody else does that,
but that is just something that I like
to do.
So, you're there, you're chilling, you're people watching,
you're chatting, maybe you're not, maybe you're just
sitting and only people watching, but you hear
something.
Whether a word, a phrase, a sentence, you
hear something, but the tone and volume is
just slightly different than the rest of the
tone and volume at that gathering.
And there could be 30, 40, 50 people
there all speaking and talking, but yet this
one instance, your ear picked up a different
tone and slight volume difference.
Now, for me, it's not an adrenaline dump,
it's not a trigger anymore, it used to
be, but it's not anymore.
It's more of kind of a superpower I
was talking about.
I'm alert, I know what I just heard
and then due to experience, I know the
potentials of what could come out of this.
So, you hear voices raised and you might
think, oh, okay, so not necessarily a heated
conversation, but just a lively conversation.
But there was something about that tone and
volume and what you heard from someone.
So, now you're on a little bit of
an alert, not hypervigilant, you're just slightly aware
that there is potential for something that you
have experienced in the past.
So, you kind of stay alert and carry
on with what you're doing and the voice
gets a little louder, the tone gets a
little more and then your fight or flight
system goes from standby to armed.
It is now ready for information from you
on whether you need to go or stay.
It's a very odd feeling when you are
somewhere having what feels like a good time
and then immediately fight or flight gets switched
to the armed mode, waiting for further input.
That's kind of a superpower.
I know it may not sound like one,
but it kind of is.
To have the experiences that we have had,
people with trauma, you are more in tune
to potential situations.
It's not that you are judging them immediately
and saying, oh, fuck, this is going to
happen because this happened.
No, our past does not necessarily dictate our
future.
You are just aware that this has happened
before and it could potentially happen again.
That's it.
That's all that is.
But learning to recognize that and trusting that
your brain is telling you, hey, let's be
a little mindful of this situation we just
heard, but not let it ruin the rest
of this gathering unless needed.
So you go on with what you're doing
and it turns out it's nothing.
It's just friends, you know, getting excited and
talking loudly over, I don't know, some sports
ball bullshit.
Who knows?
And it's nothing.
And then you're back to, you know, your
default state and your fight or flight is
no longer in armed mode.
It's now back to standby.
And that's kind of where I like to
live.
I like to be in standby and not
armed.
My fight or flight system has been stuck
on for decades.
And you can do the research.
It's very, very damaging, very damaging to your
body physically to have that stuck on for
so long.
Once you learn the triggers, once you figure
out the things that start to make you
feel a certain way, that's when things start
to become clearer and you're able to start
working to make things better.
Not necessarily better in that current situation, but
better for you and how your mind processes.
So all this is happening.
Now let's say it goes the opposite way.
The voices get louder and louder and it's
a more heated tone.
And you know it is definitely going to
be a very not pleasant time.
So what happens?
Well, our bodies have a massive adrenaline dump,
which is great.
You know, panic attack number 23,000 starts
to happen.
And I know you all know what I'm
talking about, but the most enraging part isn't
the horrible feeling that I'm going to pass
out or die or anything like that.
No, no, no, no, no.
For me, the enraging part is not knowing
what the was.
Now in this situation, it's the raised voices
and the yelling and the tone that that's
an easy one.
But when you're in situations and you cannot
figure out the trigger, that's, that's very enraging.
To put simply, that's very fucking enraging.
It's difficult to work on a trigger induced
panic attack when you seemingly cannot figure out
what the trigger is.
I've worked hard and I've identified quite a
few over the years for me.
But I still have one, just one that
gets me every single time.
And I cannot figure it out.
So picture it, Sicily 19.
No, I'm just kidding.
So picture this.
I'm at a restaurant.
Okay.
Um, and it's an Italian restaurant.
Um, it's full.
All the tables are full.
It's very loud.
There are lots of smells from home growing
up, lots of wine glasses, making noise, silverware
clanking, people scraping forks on their plates, like
nails on a chalkboard because they don't know
how to fucking eat in public.
So, you know, the usual restaurant shit.
Well, I still don't know what the trigger
was.
I don't know if it was a smell,
a sound, a color, a shape, a person,
someone's beard, how they looked, the smell of
my food, or a combination of all of
that, or just some of it.
I have no idea, but nonetheless, my body
remembered it and then boom, adrenaline dump right
then and there in the restaurant.
And I immediately wished I was not conscious
because I did not want to deal with
that again.
And I know you guys know what I
am describing.
I started to breathe deeper and it got
shallow.
I immediately got clammy and started sweating profusely.
Then the dizzy starts and then my ears
start ringing even louder.
You can barely hear the ambient sounds around
you now because your ringing is so loud.
My heart felt like it was in my
ears and then I get incredibly confused and
all of this is happening while your body
is telling you to jump out of your
skin and run away, which kind of feels
like you just got a huge shot of
steroids in your ass.
Yet your body itself doesn't want to move.
The muscles are like, nah, I'm good.
And it's almost paralyzing at times.
That adrenaline dump that happened is what's giving
you all this energy and sets your fight
or flight mode and it's ready for whatever
it's being told.
Yet sometimes it does whatever the fuck it
wants, regardless of what you told it.
It's controlled by the sympathetic nervous system and
when it's activated, all kinds of physiological shit
happens in your body.
It's as if every cell's powerhouse, mitochondria for
those who remember, have been tased, you know,
like a taser simultaneously.
But if you can burn off all that
adrenaline and noradrenaline, the panic attack will drastically
and quickly reduce.
I've done it.
It works for me.
Do jumping jacks.
Run around the house wherever you are.
If you're able to do something to burn
off that adrenaline because it also distracts you
from the said panic attack you're having and
likely at the very least it will shorten
it.
Something else that I noticed that worked for
me.
Luckily at this time I was in the
presence of a psychologist and they had me
take an ice cube out of my water
glass and put it in my hand and
close my hand and make a fist and
to focus on the cold sensation while focusing
on my breathing.
That also worked.
No rescue meds were needed.
I did not have to reach for one
of my pills and there are so many
techniques to pull yourself out of a panic
attack.
But let me be clear.
Everybody responds differently to different stimuli and the
same outcomes are not always guaranteed.
Always consult with a medical professional before you
decide to try something new.
Okay, that's all the time we have today.
Thank you everyone who joined and listened.
I truly hope you were able to take
something from this that will help you better
manage your mental health.
Please also keep in your mind that this
takes work and time.
There is no quick fix.
So please allow yourself some grace and compassion.
I hope you join again next time as
we continue dismantling the ridiculous stigma that surrounds
mental health.
And until next time, don't throat punch anyone.
Bye bye.