Hey, humans, thanks for joining my podcast.
This podcast is a place to share unedited lived experiences regarding mental health.
We'll touch on how it shows up in our lives and provide
some tips that have worked for me and others on how to manage it.
There will be strong language and definitely the
potential for disturbing and or triggering content.
Please be aware of this and mindful of
others who may be in earshot.
Most importantly, and as horribly fucking
cliche as this sounds, you really do not have to go through this alone.
And hopefully you'll see this and feel this more and more as you listen.
And hey, if this podcast isn't for you, that's fine.
There are lots of them out there.
Find one that speaks to you and helps you.
So, let's talk mental health.
And now the boiler plate and cover your ass claws
On this podcast, unless explicitly stated,
no one on this show is a medical professional in
any way, and as such, no content on
this show is intended to be, whether implied or otherwise,
to be taken as medical advice.
If you are in crisis, please call 988
or 911 or go to your nearest emergency room.
For my fellow LGBTQ Plus community, you can text start
to 678678 to
reach the amazing people over at the Trevor Project.
Or you can call them at 866-488-7386
or you can even live chat with them on
their website at chat..org.
Concertos of Chaos is sponsored by self- magnitude,
an ethical microrobusiness helping people show up as
their boldest, truest selves, at work, at play, and everywhere in between.
Founded by Maggie Green, a queer neurodivergent
brand and style strategist, self-magnitude
offers trauma-informed, affirming support for personal brand and style that reflects all of who you are
Learn more at selfagnitude.com.
And while you're there, check out Maggie's Gay It Forward initiative to support Queer Folks and Need.
There is no video for this episode because
technology and I can't, yes, me, figure out why.
So, you don't get to see my beautiful face.
Hey, everyone, thank you for joining episode six.
Involuntary harmonies, Trauma, the media,
and the soundtrack of familiar Chaos.
Ref trigger warning.
We will be touching a little on childhood trauma, but not anything specific.
Um Okay, so let's begin.
Reality TV
Most of us have seen some in one form or another.
Some of my favorites from not too long ago.
Jerry Springer, Sally, Jesse Raphael,
Phil Donahue, Ricky Lake, Montel Williams, Maury Povich, you are not the father
the many flavors of Housewives, Mary
to Medicine, The Bachelor, Bachelorette, the
last few are not ones that I've watched.
Or actually, I have married to Medicine
and some of the housewives I have seen, but not like
no, that's not true.
I have seen.
So I've seen some of the housewives that
I've seen married to medicine, but I have not seen Bachelore Bachelorette.
So some people
love reality TV.
Some people hate it, and some people are in the middle.
Why?
Well, at least two of the aspects we're going to discuss today.
And we're going to dive into why
some people simply cannot live without them
and enjoy them so much.
Or is it that they think they do?
So I liked
what I was watching because entertainment.
You know, you just, you find it entertaining.
And some of these shows, if
not all, can construct dramatic relationship narratives.
Why?
To pull you in and get you hooked on the drama.
Because let's face it, watching someone else's drama unfold
kind of takes your mind off of your own,
even if only for 30 minutes or an hour.
These dramatic narratives are intentionally amplified, you know, to get us to get viewers.
A majority of
conflicts in these shows are scripted.
Not all, but, you know, some are to get, you know, ratings to stay on the air.
Kind of, okay, so think of it like,
now, hear me out.
Don't get pissed off for all of those who like this.
But think of it kind of like professional wrestling.
It's more like a soap
opera than actual physical violence, even though they do
unintentionally, some of them get very, very, very much hurts.
So it's more like a soap opera than actual,
you know, wrestling, and all of the actors are, you know, men in tights.
Tght tights.
So the people who watch
for wrestling, they know this.
They know it's not real, yet they're still drawn
to it as if it was, or as if it were.
So, and we can discuss way later, why there are
some humans who love to watch other humans get beat the fuck up.
Another topic.
So these shows have these
psychological mechanisms
that are purposefully put in them to
influence us, kind of like subliminal messaging, but not subliminal messaging.
So what's this mean?
So we are unconsciously taking in specific dramatic
instances that we're watching on TV or a
streaming service or movies wherever you are.
And then we
take that and just broadly apply
that to other entire groups of humans.
Example.
People that watch multiple reality shows,
you know, that proudly showcase unfaithful male partners
can lead someone to uncciously believe
that most, if not all men, are prone to, you know, being unfaithful.
This constant exposure to cheating,
lying, betrayal, toxic male, bullshit, can,
you know, foster heightened anxiety, you know, in relationships,
preemptive defense mechanisms for something
that hasn't even happened, and unrealistic
expectations about, you know, partner behavior and
even potential trust issues before a relationship has even begun.
So this cognitive
distortion, love these words, allows us,
our brain, to quickly categorize the information, but
usually dangerously inaccurate
when simply based on, you know, sensationalized
representations, which is an intentional tactic to
distort and exaggerate the facts to cause a
strong emotional reaction in us and grab our
attention, which it does, but The massive problem with this,
though, is it creates distorted portrayals that make it very difficult
for some to figure out what is fact and
what is our overdramatized bullshit.
There's this thing called social learning theory,
which simply suggests that humans learn behaviors
by watching and mimicking, you know, what we see
in our personal little bubble, which literally what children do growing up.
In the context of media, though, and what we're talking about,
this means humans can often internalize those
relationship dnamics, the communication styles, and
the conflict resolution methods that you see in these shows, which
usually are not fantastic
When this, you know, is consistently portrayed
dramatically, confrontational interactions as normal,
you, especially, though some people can, even
people who have no relationship experience, some relationship,
or decades of it, can unconsciously accept
that these behaviors are acceptable and even expecteded
in these relationships.
So those who grew up
with constant conflict in traumatic environments creates
kind of an emotional baseline.
Have you ever heard of familial dysfunction?
What about familiar dysfunction, which is in the title of the this episode?
So in this context, they are very much
closely related siblings, if you will.
Familial dysfunction relates to your family
Familiar dysfunction is something that
feels known, comfortable, hence familiar.
In these situations, you can sometimes
seek out these shows or
movies in the media that damn near mirrors
your early emotional experiences
because what you saw growing up became
your emotional normalcy a swine.
For those trauma survivors, consuming these
distortions can actually be a form of of emotional regulation.
The
psychological mechanism is rooted in the concept
of mere exposure effect, which means being exposed
to something repeatedly, especially at an early age when
your brain is still developing and trying to make heads or tails of all this fucked
up world creates a sense of safety and predict
Damn it.
Creates a sense of safety.
I'm going to edit that out, and predictability.
So you find comfort in
the familiar, even though it was full of horrible, harmful dynamics.
Remember, all of this reality
consumption, can be a form of emotional regulation for us.
So, we need to break this cycle, right?
So how do we do this?
Well, through awareness.
Another word for awareness, mindfulness.
Being mindful will help you to recognize
the differences between, you know, what is true entertainment
and what healthy relationships look like.
Both can be true at the same time, yes.
It's also important to
look for patterns.
Why do you watch these these shows?
And is it only when you're sad or depressed?
Is it only when you're in a mood that you watch it?
Or do you just, you know, watch it in general just because, you know, fun, entertaininging?
Or because it's comfortable or familiar?
Think about it.
The next time you want to watch one.
Think about why you want to watch it.
If there is a why, other than it's entertaining.
Try to see if there's a reason more
so than just the entertainment of why you're drawn to want to see it.
So we have to break
the generational patterns that, you know, you grew
up with and how, how.
Okay, create healthy boundaries, something that I
was not good at. in the beginning,
but it becomes easier the more you set
Learn new strategies and,
you know, therapy, you know, professional, professional humans that can help us.
I've seen many.
They are fantastic.
I can vouch for it.
So, as we close,
my very much melodramatic, overproduced episode, let's
reflect on some of this shit.
Reity TV may just be the junk food of our emotional diet
Very tasty, very addictive, like that white cheddar popcorn.
Oh, my God.
But it's best enjoyed in moderation, unlike that white cheddar popcorn.
I eat the family size bag as a snack.
It's so fucking good.
Anyway, so if you find yourself George drawn to these
shows, like a moth to a dumpster fire
that's okay.
Sometimes watching Karen flip a table or
Morey dramatically reveal that he's not the father, well, no,
not Maury himself, but that'd be a funny episode.
It's just the catharsis that you need, right?
So life's already full of
horrible, unscripted bullshit.
So, you know, might as well watch someone else's for a change.
All right, thanks for joining me, everyone.
And here's to finding the balance between entertainment
and emotional chaos, breaking generational cycles
and most importantly, knowing when to change the channel.
While reality TV may keep us hooked, healing
is the ultimate season finale worth binging.
Okay, that's all the time we have today.
Thank you, everyone who joined and listened.
I truly hope you were able to take something from
this that will help you better manage your mental health.
Please also keep in your mind that this takes work and time.
There is no quick fix.
So please allow yourself some grace and compassion.
I hope you join again next time as we continue dismantling
the ridiculous stigma that surrounds mental health
And until next time, don't throat punch anyone.
Bye-bye