Hey, humans, thanks for joining my podcast.
This podcast is a place to share unedited lived experiences regarding mental health.
We'll touch on how it shows up in our lives and provide
some tips that have worked for me and others on how to manage it.
There will be strong language, and definitely the
potential for disturbing and or triggering content.
Please be aware of this and mindful of
others who may be in earshot.
Most importantly, and as horribly fucking
cliche as this sounds, you really do not have to go through this alone.
And hopefully you'll see this and feel this more and more as you listen.
And hey, if this podcast isn't for you, that's fine.
There are lots of them out there.
Find one that speaks to you and helps you.
So, let's talk mental health.
And now the boiler plate and cover your ass claws
On this podcast, unless explicitly stated,
no one on this show is a medical professional in
any way, and as such, no content on
this show is intended to be, whether implied or otherwise,
to be taken as medical advice.
If you are in crisis, please call 988
or 911 or go to your nearest emergency room.
For my fellow LGBTQ plus community,
you can text start to 678678
to reach the amazing people over at the Trevor Project.
Or you can call them at 866-488-7386
or you can even live chat with them on their website at chat
t.org.
Concertos of Chaos is sponsored by self- magnitude,
an ethical microrousiness helping people show up as
their boldest, truest selves at work, at play, and everywhere in between.
Founded by Maggie Green, a queer, neurodivergent
brand and style strategist, self-magnitude
offers trauma-informed, affirming support for personal brand and style that reflects all of who you are.
Learn more at selfagnitude.com.
And while you're there, check out Maggie's Gay It Forward initiative to support Queer Folks in Need.
Hey, Humans, thanks for joining us last week,
Eis episode two, conducting through chaos when your relationship with symphony plays and a toxic key.
I had some thoughts on that.
So I went ahead and recorded some things and I'm going to play them right after this.
Um, I want to thank you for your support and tuning in
Join me and my guest, Brandon
again next week for living in a new
key breaking free from life's opus.
When someone tells me, he's
not doing anything to hurt you directly, I have to take a minute.
I have to.
and point out the privilege and how
it can blind us to the horribly subtle
ways hatred spreads throughout our world.
Now, I know I probably just lost so someone, if not more,
I don't see how they're still following me, when I use the word privilege.
Well, don't freak out, because the next word's white privilege.
Yeah, go ahead.
Run to your mom, pop that tit back in your mouth, because you can't think for yourself
So, throughout history, some of our
darkest chapters, it did not begin with, you know, outright violence.
They just began with tiny, tiny little words.
And then the gradual normalization of viewing
certain groups as, you know, other.
Before that Holocaust, it
started with little tiny changes.
Casual, anti- Semitic remarks becoming
acceptable in quote unquote poloite society
small discriminatory policies that seem
insignificant in isolation and the
quiet erosion of protections that people assumed would always be there.
Before the expansion of American slavery,
it wasn't just about the brutal practice itself.
It was about the rhetoric that dehumanized black people.
So for those of you who got pissed off at that white privilege,
rhetoric is a noun, and it means the art of
effective or persuasive speaking or writing, especially
the use of figures of speech and other compositional techniques.
Now, compositional is an adjective
and in this context, meaning what we're
talking about, compositional means composed
of various elements, meaning more than one thing,
unlike what your brain can handle.
The pseudoscience that justified
their treatment, I can have a whole podcast on that alone.
Fucking idiots.
The social acceptance of viewing them as less than human.
One more time, the social acceptance
of viewing them as less than human..
This system thrived,
not just through direct violence, but also through the silent
approval of everyone who looked away.
Everyone who turned their head.
It's not going to affect me.
Why do I give a shit?
Today, when I look at my life, a
gay man, I see echoes of this.
When people who are in charge use their dog
whistles and coded language, when they embolden
those who denyy humanity,
when they roll back protections for marginalized communities,
they don't need to target us directly.
They simply need to create an environment where
your nasty ass discrimination feels and is
acceptable, where your hatred feels justified,
where your bigotry feels normal
because you don't know who you are or how to think you
have to hurt other people, which goes to that saying, hurt people, hurt people.
Every time someone who holds power suggests
that my love is less valid than anyone
else's, or that my rights don't matter or that my rights are up for debate.
You're giving permission.
You're giving permission to hate, permission to discriminate, permission
to harm, permission to hurt, permission to kill.
Permission to act on your dark
impulses that civil rights progress we thought or
should have, I should say, pushed back into the shadows.
So, no.
Maybe, you know, maybe he's not doing anything to hurt me directly.
When you ask me, why are you butt hurt?
Why are you worried?
He's not doing anything to you directly.
But yet they're creating this world where they
feel empowered to do this discriminatory bullshit.
And that, right right there, that's how every
single systemic oppression in history began.
Not with a bang, not with a huge war, not,
not with not with a memo, okay?
Did you get the memo?
Have you seen my stapler?
No.
Just a whisper, just some words, just, oh, they're different than us.
What do you think about that?
Oh, maybe we should do this.
That's how it starts.
The question is not whether someone is actively attacking you or us or anybody.
The question is whether they're making it easier for others to do the same.
And if you wait until this shit becomes
direct and blindingly undeniable,
well, we've already waited too long then.
So when someone asks you why your butt hurt, why
are you worried, he's not doing anything to hurt you directly.
Well, if
it's a friend, a family member, a preacher,
a pastor, a teacher, a quote unquote person of God.
The next time someone tells you, why are you butthurt?
They're not doing anything to you directly.
Don't don't get upset.
Don't freak out.
Don't get anxious.
Try not to have an adrenaline dump.
The truth.
Just tell them the truth.
Turn around.
Tell them the truth. speak to them like an adult.
Just say, you know what?
I hear your words, and
you're a stupid cunt.
Bye-bye.