Hey, humans, thanks for joining my podcast.
This podcast is a place to share unedited lived experiences regarding mental health.
We'll touch on how it shows up in our lives and provide
some tips that have worked for me and others on how to manage it.
There will be strong language, and definitely the
potential for disturbing and or triggering content.
Please be aware of this and mindful of
others who may be in earshot.
Most importantly, and as horribly fucking
cliche as this sounds, you really do not have to go through this alone.
And hopefully you'll see this and feel this more and more as you listen.
And hey, if this podcast isn't for you, that's fine.
There are lots of them out there.
Find one that speaks to you and helps you.
So, let's talk mental health.
And now the boiler plate and cover your ass claws
On this podcast, unless explicitly stated,
no one on this show is a medical professional in
any way, and as such, no content on
this show is intended to be, whether implied or otherwise,
to be taken as medical advice.
If you are in crisis, please call 988
or 911 or go to your nearest emergency room.
For my fellow LGBTQ plus community,
you can text start to 678678
to reach the amazing people over at the Trevor Project.
Or you can call them at 866-488-7386
or you can even live chat with them on their website at chat
t.org.
Concertos of Chaos is sponsored by self- magnitude,
an ethical microrousiness helping people show up as
their boldest, truest selves at work, at play, and everywhere in between.
Founded by Maggie Green, a queer, neurodivergent
brand and style strategist, self-magnitude
offers trauma-informed, affirming support for personal brand and style that reflects all of who you are.
Learn more at selfagnitude.com.
And while you're there, check out Maggie's Gay It Forward initiative to support Queer Folks in Need.
Today
I want to discuss a little bit on repetition and reactivity.
I'm sure you are familiar with the saying
insanity is doing the same thing over and over again
but expecting different results.
And this quote is often misattributed
to Einstein, there is zero evidence
that he has said this.
To point out, it is definitely not the quinical definition of
insanity in any way.
And whomever said this was not getting an accurate
observation to create said, quote, it's more of a legal
term than a clinical term.
So think of light bulbs, right?
We had that ass hat who likes
to steal other people's work and claim it as his own, Thomas Edison, making the light bulb.
And he is famous, we quoted, saying, " I have not failed 10,000 times.
I have successfully found 10,000 ways that will not work."
Smartphones are any technology, really
started back in the day.
We had car phones that were bricks.
They were very heavy, they were very huge.
We had backpacks that had the batteries in them,
we had giant car phones and our cars
And now they're so small, they can fit in the palm
of your hand, be concealed in your pocket, a purse,
a bag, and even your bra.
I've seen that many times.
How about aviation?
There's a lot of repetitiveness as well.
Coffee brewing methods, you know, people who
have their own coffee beans grow them, or
don't grow them, people who just make coffee at home, we
repeatedly try different methods until we get the flavor and, you know,
taste the way we want.
Musical expertise.
Hello.
I've been studying and playing for 40 plus
years and I don't know everything there is to know about music
theory or piano or any of the other instruments I used to play
And no one ever will.
But we still repeat what we do over and over
and practice until we get it.
We're not insane.
Baby humans learning to walk.
They get up and they fall.
They get up, and they fall.
They get up, they fall, they scream, wash, rinse, repeat.
Those of us who are able, eventually, we learn to walk.
All by repetition
So I have these 12 sentences
that people use when they're under pressure.
A lot of these I learned in therapy, and some of them I found
online.
So real briefly.
Number one, I need a minute to think this through.
Number two, help me understand your perspective.
Number three, that's interesting.
Can you tell me more?
Number four, I notice I'm feeling reactive
right now. and we're going to come back to that one.
Number five, let's pause and come back to this.
Number six, what would a good outcome look like for you?
Number seven, I appreciate you bringing this to my attention.
Number eight, I see this differently, but I'm curious about your view.
Number nine, can we explore other options together?
Number 10.
I'm not ready to decide yet.
Number 11.
What am I missing here?
Number 12.
Let me reflect on that and get back to you.
Now, some of these, you might
be thinking, are kind of in the same under the same umbrella, and they are.
For instance, I need a minute, let's pause.
I'm not ready.
Let me reflect and get back to you.
So some of these are under the same umbrella, yes.
But the one I want to talk about the most right now is the number four.
I notice I'm feeling reactive right now.
Okay, what's that mean?
Yes, you're right.
That's exactly what it means.
So.
I am feeling reactive right now.
The most fascinating thing happens in our brains,
neurologically, when we become reactive.
Often it's called an amygdala
hijack or emotional flooding.
This is what happens in our brains during these reactive moments.
Our amygdala, that's the part of your brain that handles
threat detection.
That's our threat detection system.
And it essentially takes over.
Then give it like a home security alarm
at your house or apartment or whatever.
More on that in a minute.
When it perceives a threat, when our amygdala perceives a
threat, whether it's physical or emotional, it
will bypass your prefrontal cortex.
I'm sorry, it can bypass your prefrontal cortex.
And your prefrontal cortex is
the part of your brain that's responsible for rational thinking and decision making
and impulse control.
So we become reactive.
What happens?
Well, as we've discussed many times before,
we have the stress hormone cortisol, and then we have adrenaline flooding our system
Blood flow actually will decrease to
your prefontal cortex, and your body emotionally
and depending on the situation, emotionally and physically, into flight
fight, or freeze mode.
I know you've heard of fight or flight, but there's also freeze.
Some people, they freeze, like a deer in the headlights.
So once we are in this armed state,
our ability to process complex information becomes immensely limited
So back to the home security system.
You come home, you open the door, and
you hear a beeping to notify you that you have about 10 or
five or 15 seconds to enter your pin number
and disable the alarm.
Or for you fancy pants people out there, you open an app
on your phone, tap on something, to disarm it, or tell
your quote unquote smart device to disable it, whatever.
Then
some people, when they get home and in
their homes, they rearm their systems, but only certain zones.
An example would be like the perimeter of their abode, the doors and the windows.
So us, our amygdala,
our threat detection system, we have the same thing.
We have our baseline vigilance, which is
our perimeter zone is armed, and that's our basicual
situational awareness.
Then we have that initial alert, which is, you know, first motion
detected, and it can be, you know, your gut feeling that, oh, shit, something's off.
There's a verification period, a delay, and
that's where you consciously, your prefontal cortex, is assessing the situation situation.
Then, well, fuck, threat confirmed, DCon 1, sound the alarm
Senor amygdala has now taken controls.
It is his airplane now.
So using that analogy, think of what's something I don't do, but probably should.
Think about going out, going to a party, visiting friends,
going out to eat, something social, something that takes you out
of your comfortable safe space.
So what do we do?
We arm our body and minds security system.
All of it.
Motion sensors, our eyes, windows and doors, the perimeter, physical, our physical selves
our personal bubble, our space.
This is our baseline vigilance.
Basic situational awareness.
Somehow, we end up finding ourselves in a situation that's
we'll say not quite ideal.
And we have picked up with our motion sensors, our eyes,
that something alerted us.
That's our initial alert.
First motion detected.
And it can be your gut telling you something's off.
But it's not imminent.
And just like, you know, your home alarm system,
motion sensors can be set to not immediately sound the alarm
when motion is detected.
And this feature is great.
It was designed for people with animals or
robot vacuums running around their homes cleaning or babies, children running around the house, etc.
So we have this alert.
We enter our proverbial pin, and we disable the alarm.
So what's our proverbial pin?
Menacting mindfulness and other techniques more on that later.
So, disabled, we're good, rearmed, going around.
Shit.
Find ourselves in another situation.
A potential thing up ahead that we're aware of.
So we have our initial alert, again, and
we see that thing is escalating, and we see that the
situation is starting to go south quickly
zero questions or doubt. verification
has happened, and we are now have a full-on detection confirmed,
and it's not a dog or evacuum or a baby are running around the house.
This is a full alarm, and the control panel
is screaming that Senor amygdala is about
to take over with zero conscious inputput
from you.
So, it's screaming.
We've entered fight or flight freeze mode, quarisol and adrenaline squirting out through our bodies.
Blood flow decreases from your prefontal
cortex, as I said before, which is where your decisions impulse to all that is handled
And complex information
is especially difficult
to handle when you're reactive.
It becomes severely limited, and extreme
cases completely non nonexistent.
Can it be a false alarm?
Of course, just like physical alarm systems and tests can have false positives
our system can be hypervigilant, over sensitive?
Seemingly broken, huh, miscalibrated?
But why?
Why is our defense system perceived as
broken or miscalibrated by us?
Well, things in our
lives, our past, past trauma, stresses
lack of maintenance, which is not practicing emotional regulation techniques.
Think of it like your pin number to disarm the alarm.
If you don't use it often
or you forget it, or your inner
situation under massive amounts of stress, you cannot disable the alarm.
Without practice, without memorizing what to do, you can't disable the alarm.
Both systems, you know, the real alarm at wherever
you are, and your on personal
alarm, your brain, your amygdala, can be recalibrated
with maintenance and adjustments, just like a physical alarm.
We upgrade the firmware in our brains with sensitivity adjustments.
And what is that?
Well, professional therapy, practicing
mindfulness, practicing mindfulness.
And
both fortunately and unfortunately, experience.
You you got to do these things and get practice doing
this and being in the situation to help you do it.
It's not fun.
I'm not going to lie.
There are times when it is really not fun
but but you have to do it.
Now, what's really interesting in this,
when your amygdo takes over, it happens in milliseconds,
and that's way faster than our consciousness little brains can process it.
By the time you're aware, you're angry
that physiological response
in your body is long already underway.
That ship has sailed.
This is why
developing awareness of your
triggers and and practicing emotional regulation techniques
are required.
They help you recognize and manage these
responses before they take full control
I notice I'm feeling reactive right now.
How many of you know what that means?
Like, how many of you
know what it is to feel that you're being
reactive versus calmly, consciously
trying to make a decision and assess?
How do we know if we're feeling reactive?
Unfortunately, sometimes
if you don't have the skills yet, it's far too late.
And after whatever has happened happened, that we
realize, fuck, I was reactive.
I should not have done that.
Why did I do that?
Why am I like this?
Don't let yourself fall into a spiral like that.
It's not, why am I like this or why are you like this?
Why are you broken?
Why am I broken?
It's not.
We're not broken.
We just have to learn and practice more skills.
That's it.
I know it sounds.
Well, it sounds easy and it sounds hard.
And it is.
It's both.
It is easy and it's hard.
I don't know how to explain that, but
it is.
Trust the process.
It is.
It's easy and it's hard.
So I want you throughout this week.
Kind of. be mindful.
And throughout your
day, this week, see if you can find a
time where something has made you feel reactive.
Now, you don't have to to go, you know, all DEFCON 1 and to
later realize, oh, I was reactive.
That's not what I mean.
I want to know if you can feel
that you are reactive, but before you
actually react and do something, before
your amygdala has been taken over.
Try and see what that feels like.
See if you can determine
when you feel reactive.
And then backtrack and find out why.
What made you feel reactive?
Did someone say something?
Did someone do something?
Did it affect you directly?
Did it affect you in indirectly?
The only way we're going
to get better at not being reactive
is identifying when we're feeling reactive.
And the only way we can do that,
aside from someone telling us, but it's too weight by them, is
to practice all of these mental health techniques.
Thank you, everybody.
I hope you have a great day.
You are not alone.
You are not a burden.
You are you.
Let's try to be happy and love who we are.
Okay, that's all the time we have today.
Thank you, everyone who joined and listened.
I truly hope you were able to take something from this that
will help you better manage your mental health.
Please also keep in your mind that this takes work and time.
There is no quick fix, so please allow yourself some grace and compassion.
I hope you join again next time as we continue
dismantling the ridiculous stigma that surrounds mental health.
And until next time
don't throat punch anyone.
Bye-bye.