(Transcribed by TurboScribe.ai. Go Unlimited to remove this message.) Hey humans, thanks for joining my podcast.
This podcast is a place to share unedited
lived experiences regarding mental health.
We'll touch on how it shows up in
our lives and provide some tips that have
worked for me and others on how to
manage it.
There will be strong language and definitely the
potential for disturbing and or triggering content.
Please be aware of this and mindful of
others who may be in earshot.
Most importantly, and as horribly fucking cliche as
this sounds, you really do not have to
go through this alone.
And hopefully you'll see this and feel this
more and more as you listen.
And hey, if this podcast isn't for you,
that's fine.
There are lots of them out there.
Find one that speaks to you and helps
you.
So let's talk mental health.
And now the boilerplate and cover your ass
clause.
On this podcast, unless explicitly stated, no one
on this show is a medical professional in
any way.
And as such, no content on this show
is intended to be, whether implied or otherwise,
to be taken as medical advice.
If you are in crisis, please call 988
or 911 or go to your nearest emergency
room.
For my fellow LGBTQ plus community, you can
text start to 678-678 to reach the
amazing people over at the Trevor Project.
Or you can call them at 866-488
-7386.
Or you can even live chat with them
on their website at chat.trvr.org.
Concertos of Chaos is sponsored by Self-Magnitude,
an ethical microbusiness helping people show up as
their boldest, truest selves at work, at play,
and everywhere in between.
Founded by Maggie Green, a queer neurodivergent brand
and style strategist, Self-Magnitude offers trauma-informed
affirming support for personal brand and style that
reflects all of who you are.
Learn more at selfmagnitude.com.
And while you're there, check out Maggie's Gay
It Forward initiative to support queer folks in
need.
Hello humans.
With me today, I have my friend Brandon.
He's gonna talk a little about himself, give
you a little info on his background, and
then a little info on his experience with
mental health.
Brandon, thank you for joining.
Thank you for having me.
It's all you, buddy.
Tell us a little about yourself and then
your experience with mental health kind of briefly.
My name is Brandon.
I used to be a network engineer, then
an AV engineer, and now just a tech
guy.
It took two heart surgeries to get me
there, though.
I was in foster care for most of
my, well, yeah, for all my teenage years
and up until I was 21.
Before that, I lived with my dad and
my stepmom, but my stepmom was really abusive.
And then my foster care system wasn't, my
foster care experience wasn't the greatest either, so.
Sadly, that's quite common.
Okay.
Anything else you want to add before you
finish?
I didn't want to interrupt you, sorry.
You know, I'm so nervous, I can't think
of anything.
This isn't live.
I mean, it's just you and I.
Like, it's not live.
No, I know.
I know, but it's going to be out
there, so they'll see you.
Yeah.
Okay.
Thank you for joining.
Today we are talking about, why would someone
have to be at my door?
Hold on.
Okay.
So, today we are talking about toxic relationships.
I wanted to start by defining the good
old interwebs dictionary.
No, it's, I think Webster's, I think.
Don't quote me.
What is a toxic relationship?
A toxic, oh, you know what?
First, let me ask you, Brandon, what do
you think a toxic relationship is?
I don't know, people who won't give in
things, would never give back, abusive relationships, manipulation.
Yeah.
Okay.
A toxic relationship refers to any relationship, whether
romantic, familial, platonic, even professional, that is emotionally
or physically harmful to one or both people
involved.
In a toxic relationship, negative behaviors, such as
manipulation, like you said, constant criticism, dishonesty, disrespect,
emotional abuse, or control, dominate the dynamic.
These behaviors undermine the emotional wellbeing of one
or both partners and can lead to long
-term damage to self-esteem, mental health, hi,
the reason for this podcast, and overall life
satisfaction.
So, that's a lot.
So, what are some key characteristics of that
entire big blurb?
Lack of respect.
So, one or both individuals are consistently either,
or consistently disregard each other's boundaries, their feelings,
or their needs.
Any or all of those.
Manipulation or control.
One person may try to dominate or control
the other through guilt, threats, or emotional blackmail.
Constant criticism is another one.
Rather than constructive feedback, criticism is harsh, very
belittling, and quite frequent.
Then you've got the lying, dishonesty, or secrecy.
There may be lies, deceit, or a lack
of transparency that, you know, kind of washes
away and erodes the trust.
Emotional or physical abuse, the most common.
This can range from verbal insults or horrible
comments, which I'm sure anyone who's experienced this
can think of a few right now, to
some serious forms, more serious forms like physical
harm or threats.
Inability to communicate healthily.
Affective and empathetic communication is typically absent in
a toxic relationship, often leading to misunderstandings, resentment,
or, you know, any conflicts, an escalation.
And then one that's common in so many
things, jealousy or possessiveness.
Extreme jealousy or extreme possessiveness can create an
unhealthy power dynamic, which will lead to emotional
distress, which then weighs on your mental health,
which then weighs on you, and then that
kind of spills out into the world around
you.
So, in these types of relationships, toxic, people
often feel tired, drained, exhausted, unhappy, unsupported.
And they may struggle to maintain their self
-esteem, their sense of self-worth, who they
are, and, hey, why am I, why am
I dealing with this?
Like, why, why am I doing this?
So, today's episode, it's important to recognize the
signs of a toxic relationship or relationships, I
guess you could be in multiple and not
know, and seek help or distance, you know,
yourself when necessary for, you know, you, personal
well-being.
Questions or comments, Brandon, on all of that?
Not particularly right now.
It's just, yeah, the long-term effects are
something people usually forget.
Yeah.
Once you're away from it, they just, oh
yeah, everything's better, but it doesn't work that
way.
Yeah.
I don't want to say it's a culture
of people, but there's some people who think
if you don't complain about something, I guess,
a lot, then either the pain or whatever
issue is, has stopped or gone away.
And it's like, no, I just don't want
to complain about it every day and just
kind of be seen or labeled as, oh,
you know, there's Christopher, he's here to complain
again.
Yeah.
So, you know, people kind of keep it
inside.
Okay.
So, for you, you can keep in your
mind's eye any relationship that you figured out
was toxic, and then you can talk about
it.
But my first question was, you know, what
specific thing flew you in that whatever relationship
you're about to talk about was toxic?
Probably the fear, just the distress of it.
Like I used to think about my dad
and him not being there and just terrified
of what would happen with my stepmom.
She was very manipulative and good at hiding
and intimidating me into not saying anything for
a long time.
Wow.
So the fear of abandonment by your dad.
Yeah.
I was always worried.
I'm not afraid.
I wasn't afraid that he would leave, more
of like afraid if he died or for
whatever reason wasn't still ultimately a form of
abandonment, not, you know, not intentional, but yeah.
Yeah.
You just heard the fear of being left
alone with your mom.
Stepmom.
Sorry.
I apologize.
So what I want to say patterns, but
every situation is kind of different.
But were there any patterns or that you
can think back on now patterns that you're
like, oh yeah, that was toxic.
Oh yeah.
That's not something that should have happened to
a child.
That, that was toxic.
Were, did you see any patterns going back
over however long?
Well, that's the manipulation.
So like I was intimidated from saying anything
and then she obviously wasn't going to say
anything.
So it was just a cycle of hiding
it from my dad.
Um, like one time she, uh, she thrown
a spoon at me and it, it hit
my eyebrow and left a big gash.
Um, and I ended up telling my dad
that it was my glasses that had pushed
against my face.
I'd like hit them hard or something.
Um, cause I was still just so afraid
of telling him what actually happened.
But you weren't afraid of his reaction.
You were afraid of her reaction.
Yeah.
I was afraid of her reaction.
And then I was also afraid that it
would hurt him.
Right.
Cause you know, he's the one biological parent
that I have.
And how old were you at this time?
I think that happened when I was around
10 or 11.
The whole thing started when I was around
five.
Okay.
So fear being left alone, not knowing what
your stepmother would do.
Got you.
And then fear of telling your dad because
you didn't know what she would do, but
also putting your dad's feelings before yours.
Um, unfortunately, um, that's where we've learned these
bad habits or not bad habits.
These mental health traits is where we get
them is our, our wonderful childhoods.
Um, yeah.
Um, so manipulation is the pattern.
Yeah.
Um, I'm surprised.
I know manipulation was in the definition, but
I'm actually surprised it wasn't talked about more
and I'm the host.
I should have done that note for future.
Um, so at that time, either, uh, it's
kind of young five, um, maybe when you
got older or older by meaning like seven
or eight or nine, how did it start
to, or when did you notice it affecting
your mental health and how it was kind
of spilling out into your outside relationships?
Um, I kind of realized a little earlier
that it, that it was bad, which I
mean, it's hard not to think something's bad
being abused.
Um, that's true.
I don't know.
I didn't repeat the question.
I already forgot.
It's okay.
Okay.
Um, at what age, not at what age,
um, when did you start noticing that what
was happening to you was affecting your mental
health?
And then also if it started to spill
out and started affecting other relationships you had
with people probably around second grade, um, in
second grade, I know that we moved away
from my, from my dad's family and they
were kind of like, they didn't know about
it at that time.
Um, but they were positive and loving, uh,
all those things.
So when we moved away from them, I
was more isolated and more able to recognize
what was going on.
Oh, okay.
Okay.
I gotcha.
Um, one of the, I, I looked up,
um, some common questions that are asked to
people about mental health.
Um, and one of them I wanted to
ask because when I first read it, I
laughed.
Um, and as I sit here and stare
at it again, it's not funny because I
think I get it in a different way.
But the question is, how long did it
take you to heal from this toxic relationship?
And then how did you heal?
Like, what did you do so to speak
that, uh, made you heal?
And the first time I read this, I
laughed cause I'm like, do you really heal
from something that traumatic?
But then I started thinking, well, what's the
point in, in therapy, um, forever, you know?
And why, why are you going through all
of this if you can't heal?
Um, and of course we just got the
notification about this app that our time limit
is coming up.
So if it cuts out, I'll just restart
it.
Um, and we'll just finish and I'll edit
it in.
So go ahead.
How, how, how did you heal?
How long did it take you to heal?
I mean, I'm, I'm still healing.
Um, it was really weird.
It didn't really, um, I mean, it did
a little bit, but I was probably really
good until, uh, so say around 25 or
27.
Um, it really hit my mental health then
it was kind of a delay.
And then I had to go to therapy,
um, for a long time.
I was put on suicide watch a couple
of times.
Wow.
Yeah.
It was, it was just bad, especially just
the not expecting it.
Haven't been so fine for so long.
Right.
And then just suddenly having a huge mental
breakdown and realizing that it was CPTSD and
now I'm, you know, bipolar, um, just from
all that, it all stems from that.
And it stems from my mom going away.
Um, yeah, stems from trying to tell people,
but not getting listened to.
Yeah.
Not being heard.
Um, all those things still impact me.
I still worry about not being listened to.
I still, you know, I still think about
all these things.
Um, but I have to, well, through therapy,
I learned how to rephrase the, the context
in my head.
Yes.
Reframing is amazing.
So this started at five and you're how
old now?
33.
33 and still healing.
So my advice to anyone, cause we, we
gotta go here in a second.
My advice, if I was going to give
someone advices, this is not something that you
can heal from immediately.
Um, look how, how, you know, how long
Brandon's been, been going at this.
Um, so don't, don't give up.
Uh, don't, don't give up.
Brandon, anything you want to say, piece of
advice, if you could.
Um, keep the healthy relationships.
Uh, like, you know, we all have, we
all know there's like two, three people in
your, in your life that probably put in
more effort than everybody else.
I mean, not everybody else is like mistreating
you or bad or whatever, but those, there's
two, three people that really make you have
fun and keep you positive.
They're, they're, those are the most important relationships
to absolutely the combating these kinds of issues.
Yeah.
You once said, live your life around your
mental health and not let your mental health
tell you how to live your life.
Something along those ways, that just kind of
sounded like what's his face on the moon,
but that's not what I was, it's not
what I was going for.
But you said it.
Build your life around, um, around your mental
health and your mental health issues and not
necessarily around what everybody expects you to do,
because, um, you know, once you're impacted by
these kinds of things, you're just not like
everybody else.
I mean, you can, you can still blend
into society and do all those things, but,
um, you still probably hiding, um, big aspects
of your problems, which, I mean, I don't
go around telling everybody that dealt with child
abuse and those things, but, you know, it's
not my, not my elevator pitch, but right.
You know, there's two, three people that you
tell, um, and talk to about those things.
It's just important.
Maybe next time or another episode could be
how to build your life around your mental
health versus letting it rule you because you're
actually doing that right now.
Um, and that would be awesome to talk
about and how that ties into making your
mental health better.
Um, so yeah.
Um, Brandon, thank you so much for joining
me today.
Um, I cannot wait until, you know, you
come back and we talk about, um, how
to build your life around mental health.
That's an awesome topic, but I'll have to
make it a musical name, but yeah.
Um, so yeah, thank you so much for
joining anything you want to say before we
go.
I don't know if that was all about,
um, toxic relationships or not.
I'm sorry.
Um, I kind of went down a tangent.
That's the whole point.
Organic.
No, no script organic, except for the definition
organic.
All right.
Thank you so much, Brandon.
Have a great day.
And I hope to see you next time.
Everybody join me again next week, and we
will talk about how to possibly maybe next
week, how to build your life around mental
health.
Um, have a great day, everybody.
Bye Brandon.