Hey, humans, thanks for joining my podcast.
This podcast is a place to share unedited lived experiences regarding mental health.
We'll touch on how it shows up in our lives and provide
some tips that have worked for me and others on how to manage it.
There will be strong language and definitely the
potential for disturbing and or triggering content.
Please be aware of this and mindful of
others who may be in earshot.
Most importantly, and as horribly fucking
cliche as this sounds, you really do not have to go through this alone.
And hopefully you'll see this and feel this more and more as you listen.
And hey, if this podcast isn't for you, that's fine.
There are lots of them out there.
Find one that speaks to you and helps you.
So, let's talk mental health.
And now the boiler plate and cover your ass claws
On this podcast, unless explicitly stated,
no one on this show is a medical professional in
any way, and as such, no content on
this show is intended to be, whether implied or otherwise,
to be taken as medical advice.
If you are in crisis, please call 988
or 911 or go to your nearest emergency room.
For my fellow LGBTQ Plus community, you can text start
to 678678 to
reach the amazing people over at the Trevor Project.
Or you can call them at 866-488-7386
or you can even live chat with them on
their website at chat..org.
Concertos of Chaos is sponsored by self- magnitude,
an ethical microrousiness helping people show up as
their boldest, truest selves at work, at play, and everywhere in between.
Founded by Maggie Green, a queer neurodivergent
brand and style strategist, self-magnitude
offers trauma-informed, affirming support for personal brand and style that reflects all of who you are
Learn more at selfagnitude.com.
And while you're there, check out Maggie's Gay It Forward initiative to support Queer Folks in Need.
Hello, everybody.
We are talking about building your life
around your mental health.
We touched briefly on it last week with Brandon here,
my guest, and I decided that
would be a great next episode.
I was thinking maybe doing a bonus or like a behind the scenes thing, but this is
neither because it
just ties into the topic mental health and
you know, how do we deal with it?
How do we live with it?
Most people fight it.
I've been fighting it decades
And I don't want to anymore.
I don't don't want to fight it.
I want to work with it.
It's clearly here to stay.
It has good days and bad days, but
I need to stop fighting it.
So, Brandon, welcome again.
Tell us.
how you got the idea of building your life around mental health.
Yeah, we'll just start there.
How'd you get that idea?
Like, what clicked or what made you think, oh, this isn't working anymore.
Let's try this.
Well, I wanted to live nomatically
for basically my entire adult life.
But when
when I had the second surgery, the second heart surgery
and all of that went down, I just, I couldn't ignore that impulse anymore.
It just, you know, it's time to be happier.
And then also the infection was super dangerous.
The whole reason I had the second surgery was that infection.
You brushed with death twice, survived.
And that's when you decided, I need to make some
changes because you're not happy and you need to live your life the way you want to.
Yeah.
So explain how you were living your life and then
we know what was the c was for the change.
So explain how or how you were living and
now how you are transitioning to where you want to be.
So before I've always had engineer type positions
NIT.
Yeah.
So I started out as a network engineer and
had a mental health collapse when that was going on.
So I switched to
a job that I thought I would like more in classroom design
and managing contractors and all of that.
But it still was I was just still struggling with it.
I don't really fit into the
the normal societal life where I have
this big long career because I don't know.
My mind's just not wired for that.
Tell just briefly what classroom design is so people know.
You work for a university, so let them know what classroom design means..
So I would
draw a blueprint or really have kind of blueprints for the room layout.
I would create wiring diagrams and then transpose those
that all that all the
wiring diagrams compassed onto the blueprints.
So the contractors install it.
And then I would
follow the project and make sure the contractors were doing it correctly.
I was also doing the scopes of work.
And this was all for setting up network infrastructure, audio audio video in a classroom?
This was when I was in the classroom technology.
Right.
So was it like a professor would say, hey, this classroom sucks.
I need this in here.
Or upgrgrades.
Usually it would be like the department.
Oh, okay.
Okay.
Or sometimes we were just doing mass upgrades and it was really
my decision and my supervisor's decision.
Okay..
So you were a network engineer and
then did not like switch to classroom design?
Don't really fit that.
Continue.
Yeah.
And I I found every time I got myself into a routine
like just like the normal routine, I would just fall apart.
Even if I like like getting up, getting dressed, going to work work, come home, rinse repeat.
Yeah.
So, I mean, even even though like at
the beginning of these jobs, I was really happy and exciting.
It just wore off.
And then I would lapse again.
I Yeah, I know that feeling.
Kind of like.
Like a honeymoon period.
Yeah.
What they would say, you know, relationships have that honeymoon phase.
Most every job I've worked
um, well, all, but I. Sorry.
All but one or two jobs were IT.T.
And I loved them all in the beginning.
Like it was fantastic.
And I don't know if it was just because, oh, new job, exciting.
Or if it's
new job exciting, great.
I love what I do, but then something, either the
people, the environment, or my mental health, it's no longer fun.
And then it becomes very, I get very irritated, very agitated.
You know, people are calling for help and the last thing I want to do is help them
And I don't know if
that's my mental health or
maybe those positions weren't for me, because
in general, I've never really liked to deal with the general public.
But as you, yeah, maybe.
But as you know, most IT people,
we start at the help desk when we get our foot in the door in this world.
And
that was fun.
I loved it because I love helping people.
But it started to get irritating and
resentful that these people don't know how to do what they're calling me
to know how to do.
And my job is to help them do what they don't know how to do.
Sometimes you're just like, you know, Google's a thing.
Right.
But
right.
But that's what we're there for.
That's what the help desk is for.
You know, you don't, I don't, I don't.
I've had someone call me and ask where a bathroom was in
a building that I used to work at because they didn't know who else to call.
So they called the help desk.
I had some people.
I had somebody call and asking where to park
Yes.
Yeah, the IT help deskk.
One-stop shop.
It's like you're concierge, wherever you are.
Okay, so back where we were.
Engineer?
No.
Classroom tech, no.
Now you are
realizing you don't, it does doesn't fit you.
So continue for me.
So I just, I have all this
weird knowledge about IT and different aspects of
IT, you know, programming, networking, um, design and all that.
So I took all my experience and all
of my, my education and got a help desk job.
But I was able to find a part-time
one and it's a it's a remote position
Right now.
Yeah.
Which are the two things I wanted more most.
So I, yeah, I was happy to switch.
My doctor was happy.
I switched.
All in all, everybody is happier.
Yeah.
I. When I, when, when COVID
happened and we and most, a lot of people switched to working from home, I was so happy.
Yeah.
Most IT people, though, you know, we can work from home, depending
on what our job is, because we can just remote in and do what we need to do
I noticed
my mental health improved when I had to stop going
in and I could be in my own comfortable, safe environment
at home, wearing pretty much whatever I want from the waist down
just be careful when you stand up.
If you're on a virtual call, call people.
Yeah.
So my mental health, it improved because I'm someone I don't
uh, it's not a need.
I just don't, have, um, the ability
to be in someone's presence physically doesn't really exist with me.
Like, if I never saw another human in person
I, it wouldn't phase me.
Virtual is plenty for me.
If I can see you and we can chat and it's real time, that's enough. for me.
I don't I don't have to be in your presence to feel something.
But on the flip side, I have noticed when
I am physically around people, I do get a
little more of a boost in my mental health.
So it's a doubleged short.
It's like, I don't want to be around you people, but
because you annoy me and my mental health suffers.
But being around you helps my mental health a little bit.
So what the hell are you supposed to do when you don't want to be around
people, but you have to be around people?
It's.
Do what?
Answer phones.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay, so you took all your skills, got this current job
working from home, and you like this better.
I I'm sure.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
I make a lot less money, but I'm also.
But you're happier.
I'm so much happier.
And I don't deal with the same levels of stress
Like my job is almost no stress.
I when I hang up the phone on somebody, it's over.
My part's done.
It goes on to next person.
Well, the problem's not sol.
I can do that.
I always had this horrible, horrible..
Actually, it's not a horrible thing to have, but follow through like, what they call follow through.
Even though I'm done, where where we?
See, that's what happens when I go off
on a tangent.
We work help us now.
You work I work help desk now, yes.
And from home and you noticed it is better for your mental health.
Why, though?
Like what, what aspect is better for your mental health?
Well, I don't have the stress or the pressure.
I I don't have to come in and do the same thing nearly every day.
I just kind of.
So it's not monotonous?
Your calls are different every time?
No, not really, but I only have to do it 20 hours a week.
Oh.
Yeah, it's just just not as main.
It's not the main focus of my life anymore.
I don't have to work a third of my days.
Yeah, working to live
or living to work.
I never get those right.
So yeah, I might make dozens of dollars, but I'm happier.
And that's the thing.
My, you know, I've had a job where I had
a very good salary, but I wasn't happy.
And then Lou said job, and
then some other things happen, and you go on this spiral.
But overall,
I'm happy.
Like, I don't.. not having the stress,
like, of something like that, the anxiety,
the horribleness that it does to
your body, the adrenaline dumps, the panic its attacks,
the tension, the sucking your tongue and holding
it to the roof of your mouth because you're so stressed out, grinding your teeth
gzing your hands, keeping your neck tense in your shoulders,
all of that is mental health manifested physically, all of it.
And some most people don't even realize they're doing it.
And staying tense like this
eight hours a day while you're working, not so good for the body.
Not so good at all.
Okay, so what are you doing then?
So, yeah, now I have a remote job. oil.
I only work part-time.
And now my partner and I are we're renovating
in our B, and we we're just going to live in it and travel.
Talk about that.
So yeah, that's actually one of the main reasons why I wanted a part-time
remote positions, because I don't know, I've always been drawn to a nomadic lifestyle.
Really, I think it has hard to do with like my trauma and then part to do with
being bipolar.
I just don't quite
survive well into regular societal life.
So yeah, now we're working on the RV.
I'm way more excited for the future.
I don't picture myself in five
years doing the same thing and being stressed out.
So that's been great.
So you actually have a vision of the future that's no
longer stressful or anxious.
Exactly.
It's just, yeah, it's just exciting.
So when you say a nomadic lifestyle,
you talk more about that.
Like, you're not just going to up and move into an RV and
then just travel the country and never, I guess,
have like a quote unquote home base or something.
You still plan to have like, you know, home base.
If we're going to have a home base, I don't know how often we'll be here.
But in America, being
homeless is apparently a bad option.
Being un housed, yeah.
They get mad.
It's best to have a physical address somewhere.
Right.
Because society doesn't like nomads.
You know, we're
So you have an RV that
you purchased a used one, and you gutted it, right?
Inside.
And I know you just told me you did,
you had to rewire the wiring harness for the engine because you
put, well, you tell, you talk about it.
Walk us through what you did from buying me in until right now.
So we bought it.
We wanted a something not normal, something cool.
So we bought a a 1972 RV.
So it's got, it's really cute.
It's got all kinds of character, but it also gets like four miles to now.
The thing that thing is never met a gas station.
It doesn't like.
Is it gas or diesel?
Yes.
G. It's a big block.
Have you thought about converting it?
To diesel?
Well, not straight diesel.
Like the hybrid one where you can just go get like
french fry oil and, you know, obviously strain and filter.
Yeah, you can clean, but I met something like that.
You have to do.
You have to have a diesel to do that.
Oh, you have.
But what I am doing, I took a, I got an engine out of a
just a Chevy, 2500, and I'm really builtbuilding it.
And I'm just going to do an engine swap with
a modern engine and get g injection and cruise control.
All of the nice things, a check engine light.
That light that's always on no matter how new your car is.
And then maybe get nine to 11 miles down.
Maybe.
What?
I can't even scroll back in the captions.
I really don't like these captions.
But I that's how I...
Oh, someone asked, how do you do a podcast through your death?
Well, I do have some residual hearing, so this
monitors I have on my ears are jacked up to 10.
They' as loud as they go.
Plus, I have my hearing aids under these.
So it's also being amplified.
So that's how I do it.
And then I rely on the captions on the screen.
So any of my guests who don't speak slowly or clearly
No.
No, it's doing good with you, Brandon.
It typically does good with you, but I have some friends that call.
It just doesn't, it doesn't do well, which makes it impossible.
Anyhow, so you got an engine, Chevy.
You put it in here.
You redid the harness.
You said you're going to do aftermarket stuff
You said you mentioned one of them, cruise control.
Yeah.
So the engine I have is all electronically controlled.
So the throttle the throttle controlled.
Fly by wire?
Let's drive by wire.
So
it's really easy to make those things work.
Right.
I mean, you know, as well as I do in the tech field,
adding more complexity to something makes it even worse when it breaks.
So did this, this engine has ODB2 connection, right?
Yeah.
Or is it OBD2?
I don't, you know what I mean.
So it does.
Okay.
So.
I just have I just have a microphone slashcamera, potato combination.
Potato combination
Okay.
So what are your plans?
Do you have a date, like a rollout date, where wheels up, we're out?
Wheels.
Not specifically.
We're hoping to get it done before winter.
You know winter's here, right?
It just snowed yesterday
Yeah, but we we didn't originally plan to gut it all at once.
We were just going to do the bedroom and then do the rest of overtime.
Oh.
But
we found mice nest or a rat nest.
So we're just like, well, we'll just gut it.
Yeah.
And I'm I'm really glad we did because there there was a lot, there was a lot more.
Found some things you didn't know were going to be there.
Yeah.
That's the way it goes when you're working on something that's over 50 years old.
Hell, working on anything nowadays,
you'll find things that you did not expect to be in there and
that most times shouldn't be in there.
So is your plan, like, you don't really have a plan.
You're just going to go do you?
Or just drive the country?
Do you have a route or are you just going to go south, north,heast, west, whatever.
That's why it fits into me.
No plan.
Just go and see what happens.
My manic episodes can now just be, hey, let's go to this city.
That is so appealing to me.
Like,
and you'll still be able to work, right?
Remotely with.
Yeah, I'll have a Well, we have the TMobile
5G. And we can just take it where we go and I can
I can answer calls.
It's not glamorous, but I can answer calls.
I know quite a few people who in IT work
remotely, who are a nomadic lifestyle.
They you know, they have a home or they have a condo or something,
but they prefer to spend the majority of their time traveling.
Yeah. you meet new people
and you get away from people you don't like
And that's how you find more like-minded people is
you get out and you socialize, which..
What?
I More than forward to being able to tell the people who call
me for tech support, my personal life, being like, you know, I'm in California.
I don't want to tell you.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So we don't have that problem here in California.
Sorry
Let me give you another number to call.
His name is.
Just kidding.
You know where I was going with that.
A little inside Joe. Can't share that.
I do that to the IT telemarketers that call my office phone.
I send them that way.
Perfect.
So So, yeah, that, that sounds appealing.
I know there's other people out there that sounds appealing.
And I'm sure there are people out there who think, I can't do that.
I can't do that at this stage in my life.
I'm too young or I'm too old or, well, I
have this or I don't have enough money or
walk us through this
because, I mean, let's be honest, you're not rich.
I know you.
You're not even close to rich.
Dozens of dollars.
Right, right.
I mean, it costs more to
file the taxes in an envelope than it does does to get back.
Dozens of dollars.
What's your plan?
Do you have a plan for like income.
You know, you got so you have your gas for the vehicle.
You have insurance for the vehicle.
You have whatever maintenance comes up.
You have, you know, which is brakes, tires, oil,
transmission fluid, belts
um serpentine, you know, all these different expenses
and you're in a, what, 30-some year old RV?
52 Oh, sorry.
What year is it?
1972.
72.
Okay, okay.
Yeah, so you have this old piece of ancient history that
knock on wood could just fail at any moment.
Do you have any plans for that?
Like, I think, I feel like it would be a fun, cool thing, but like,
what if it just breaks down, right?
You blow a hose or something and you, you, it's no big deal.
You don't need to find a hotel.
You live in it
Yeah, in most car issues, I can I can fix myself.
Because I've been working on cars just about my whole life.
Which is another plus is having the
automotive electronic experience, the
IT experience, all of that, mechanic experience experience is great
for people who want to live on the road.
For people who don't have those skill sets, but still
want this nomadic life, well,
like my partner, she is
really into art and crocheting and those kinds of things.
So what we're going to do with what she wants to do is start
a a web store to
complement her, because she goes to markets now.
She's to compliment the market, she wants to start a YouTube channel
and link her store to that so she
can start selling her work to more people.
So that's her plan.
And then my plan is I, you know, I got this remote position.
I can keep doing it.
Right.
And I'm also
able to do finished carpentry.
So I I
like to restore furniture and stuff and flip it.
And then every once in a while I'll take a commission job.
So are you going to have like a
a website for yourself or for your
brand of nomadic lifestyle so that like when you go places, you can
set up side jobs to make a little money, right?
Yeah, yeah, we can do that.
I hadn't figured out the specifics on that part.
For now, I'm just going to
just lean on my current, just my
shore income.
Right, right, right, right, right.
And then I also had a nest egg.
Okay.
Well, that's always good.
Do you have any advice?
We're not leaving, but do you have any advice for people who don't have these skill sets but still want this wife?
Like someone who's like, oh, God, what if it breaks down?
What if this happens to my, I don't know anything about this.
What do I do?
Any advice for people like that?
I mean, just, just look for something that
you can do remotely or, or
find a hobby that you really like and and find a way to monetize it.
No, no, no.
I mean people who are committed to doing this nomadic
lifestyle and traveling in an RV or converted bus or whatever they decide
But they have no mechanical skills.
They have nothing like that, like nothing.
But they still want to do this.
There's a lot of people in the van life community that have that problem.
not a problem.
It's just don't have that dealset.
Yeah.
It's a problem that breaks down.
Right.
Can be, yeah.
But they usually go and find like a
a little bit newer of a vehicle.
Okay, so you would recommend some newer.
And then they also, you know, There's
always mom and pop mechanics.
What about insurance?
Is it, you know, I need to talk to you about your expired car warranty.
Well, with
an RV, you can ensure it as an RV,
which is a good amount cheaper.
Does it cover everything inside of it, or do you need renter's insurance?
Like, I don't or like, how do you call owners insurance an RV?
I think it just depends on the insurance plan.
Okay.
For us if we had it like
burned to the ground for whatever reason.
Knock on wood, not putting that out.
I think we would probably just lose what's in it.
But, you know, it's just stuff.
Fair.
It is just stuff.
As long as the animals got out.
And you guys.
Yeah.
That's move. important.
So you don't have, you you
don't have any plans or like a set.
Like, I want to go see the biggest ball with yarn or I want to go see the world's
largest frying pan because that's something I would do.
I would go travel to all those places
We'll probably go to those places, but it'll just be, you know, whenever we want.
Spontaneous, sporadic.
Mostly.
It's probably depend on what's making me manic at that moment.
That's fair.
And that full circle now, now we can go back into this.
Wving your wife your life around around your mental health.
So how often do you think you get manic?
Or how often do you know you get manic?
Sorry, not think?
Every
Probably around six to eight weeks.
Sometimes a little more than that.
Out of a year or at once, consecutively.
Oh, just
between.
Yeah, I think that was an underestimate now.
But did you mean that, like, total in
a year, you get manic about total time, six to eight weeks,
or do you mean you stay manic for six to eight?
weeks?
Well, I was thinking about it, and I get
manic probably four weeks from the last time ends.
So time.
So, like, let's say I have a manic episode that's two weeks long.
I'll probably skip out until
another four weeks after that..
So it's like six weeks that way.
So you have manic episodes that last two weeks, up to two weeks?
Sometimes.
Whoa.
Oh, I've lost thousands
of dollars to manicica.
Wow, and that's very common, too.
The people
captions said mannequin.
Good Lord.
Yeah, I think I added it up in my head earlier,
and I've lost about probably at least 20 grand.
In the span of what time?
Since I was, I think around 25.
25?
So 7 years years?
No.
Eight years?
Getting old.
Right.
Eight years.
So what is what does mania look like for you?
Is it the same every time?
Or is it.
Sometimes I like one time I went on a minimal minimalist
kick and I threw just about all my belongings away
And that went well.
Did it?
Did it go well?
And then, I mean, I bought, I purchased like
so many project vehicles during manic episodes.
There's only one of them I don't regret.
And that's, that's the Jeep.
The Jeep.
I knew you were going to say The Jeep.
Yeah.
The one manic episode that paid off in the longer end.
Wow.
So is it.
Is it kind of like a retail therapy when you're manic?
Or do you do retail therapy even when you're not manic?
It's not really retail therapy.
I get obsessed with like a certain thing or
a certain hobby or a certain.
And I
I just go all in and then I want to get the best
of the best and I buy it, and then I use it for like a week.
Or I stay excited about it for a week.
Right.
And that's once again, at my hand, it's like, oh, yeah, who cares?
Do what?
And that's the mania for you?
Sometimes, sometimes I just go like on a
crazy cleaning spree where I'll pull everything
out of the drawers and organize everything.
And
it really.
And you would.
I'm sorry, it depends.
And you attribute this to
Manic episodes, the bipolar, and not, say, ADHD or autism?
Or a combination of all three.
My therapist thinks it's
from bipolar, but also like CPTSD
has very similar symptoms.
Avo.
And then I'm just kind of realizing here recently,
enough people have mentioned it to me.
I didn't realize I might be autistic.
See, everybody else seems to know.
I mean, everyone else seemed to know about me as
well until, you know, a diagnosis.
Yeah, you're so autistic, Brandon.
You are like hardcore.
A lot of people I know are, and it's funny that the people, like you say, keep good people in your life.
Those are the good people that are in my life,
the ones that kind of think like me or at the very least
understand how I think..
And you, you said that., I think I just said that keep
the people, the good people in your life.
Yeah, you know, the people who bring positivity
Right.
And that you can confide in.
Someone you can trust and that you can, right, right, right, right.
And I was actually talking today, like, when is
talking about something become complaining about something?
And as an example, I was talking about this morning
we were talking about hearing and how there are some days
like today, you know, I just
cried most of today because I was
trying to listen to some music and I was then I was
going to try to work on a song on, well, a few songs I was composing before all this fun shit happened.
But it doesn't sound the same to me.
It's not.
It's just not the same.
And most days, I'm just like, oh, well, I mean, this is it.
Radical acceptance, right?
This is your life now.
But then there are some days like today where I can't block, you know, the thoughts.
Yeah.
And I just, what can you do?
Right?
So I just go with it.
I'm not fighting it anymore.
So I just sat here and cried.
That's all I did.
We sat right here in this chair and fucking cried.
Um, with music blasting in my monitors and my hearing aids trying to
get back a feeling of the times when it was like normal, so to speak.
Yeah, so we were talking about that.
And I'm like...
Who do I talk to this about?
Everyone I know already knows.
Like everyone I know knows about this.
So if I talk about it every day to get it off my
chest, when is it complaining?
And like, I'm always afraid someone's going to be like, oh, there's Christopher.
He's complaining again.
And about, you know, he's hearing.
I would say complaining starts when you
have control over the situation, or
at least some control over the situation.
In my own.
Explain that.
So, like, you're hearing loss.
You have no control over that.
There's nothing you can do about it.
It's just a huge impact on your life right now.
And in the future
I mean.
As a classical piano for 40 years, yeah.
I mean, I would expect you to be upset and I wouldn't classify that as complaining.
It's so much more than than upset, Brandon.
Yeah, well, I know.
It's, it's like,
There are no words.
I can't find a word to mean how I feel.
But I I mean, it ruins your life.
The way you are with music.
It just, it ruins what you mean as life.
My identity for 40 years was piano, piano, piano, piano, piano, piano, piano, piano
And that's why I wouldn't classify it as
a complaint as more of it's like like a
huge issue you're dealing dealing with.
But how do you talk to this do you talk
about this so that you're getting it out?
because it affects you every day, every second that I'm awayake.
How do you get this out and process
it without sounding like you're just complaining about
the same thing over and over again?
Because, right, it's always going to be about the same thing that's
consuming.
It's why there's two or three people are important because
like if you talk to me about it, I'm never going to think to just complainingaining.
It's, you.
Yeah.
It's huge.
It is.
And when I'm told to talk about it, I
don't know what to talk about, if that makes sense.
Like, I don't, like, what do I say?
Okay, mers, the tinitis is so loud.
I can't really hear anything else.
Then it drops again, and then I had to get new hearing
aids, and now music is like not even existing in my life anymore.
What do you say and to talk about it when people already know?
I mean, and that, anything mental health that
somebody may know about you, how do you talk about it without it
coming off that you're just complaining?
It's really a great area.
It's hard.
And Don Yars even said it today,
it depends on the person you're talking to.
You know, if they're taking it that way.
He's like, it just depends.
And you can't really, you can't control how someone takes something.
You can clarify before you say something, like pre
or you can clarify after you say something.
But in that moment, there's no way someone's just going to perceive what they perceive.
Yeah, and like when I have some
kind of trigger, well, triggers a strong word.
When I have something that really
makes me remember things from my past that were challenging.
I mean, my response to that, I don't think would be a complaint.
It would just be
something that I like, I don't have a lot of control over how I feel.
I mean, we do, but also there's there's circumstances that we have no control over.
Right.
That's where radical acceptance comes into play.
You started to say trigger and then said, no, why did you change it?
Well, I don't..
I feel like trigger is something..
I don't know.
I like I don't like the.
I guess I don't enjoy or I don't like
the concept of triggers.
I feel like that puts a taboo on some things.
You know, if you're going to get emotional, it's going to happen.
If you don't want to be emotional, then I don't know.
But
Well, I think in the context of mental health, trigger means
a specific thing that breaks up a traumatic.
I guess the way I think about it is that
I don't mind triggers because it makes me communicate
things and de-stigmatize things
from my past.
I don't, I feel like there's a stigma in
being a victim a lot of times in cases of abuse and such like that.
And I just, I just don't like people walking on the eggs shoulders around me.
If it happens, it happens kind of thing.
So I guess they could still be considered triggers.
I just don't I don't view it as a
thing to hold me down or view it as a thing that I get to communicate to people
Right.
That's a good way of reframing that.
Wow.
Hmm.
Yeah, I still call them triggers.
But I never really put it any thought into the actual word.
I guess I see triggers and opportunities.
Right.
Okay.
Triggers as opportunities.
Yeah, when I, something triggers and I have a panic
attack, first thing I think of is not, oh, here's an opportunity to figure out what happened.
Nope, that's not what happens when you have a panic attack, unfortunately
But that's interesting.
A trigger has a room for room to whatever you said.
It's a room for
it's room for understanding..
Okay.
You know, it's like you're going to have a
visceral visceral reaction oftentimes with
a trigger, but I don't know.
I just don't view that as
a thing I want to avoid.
I view it as a thing that I want to..
Oh, yeah, yeah.
No way. portray
Right.
It's you want to work through them because
you want to identify them so that they don't become triggers anymore.
Yeah.
It's complicated.
I mean.
It is.
No, it is.
I mean, some people avoid trigers like to play.
Right.
I just want people to be just to be around me.
I don't want or like to be themselves.
And I don't want them to walk on eggshells because they might
trigger me.
Well, but that's part of life.
Like, we can't tell everyone we know, hey, these are my triggers.
And you can't tell everyone you interact with that.
Maybe you're close or a friend, you know, those people you were talking about.
But once you get really good at reframing things in your mind
triggers become different, I guess.
No, no, no.
Yeah.
I never thought about reframing a trigger once
you identify it to help lessen it and make it not a trigger anymore.
Never thought about that.
Because I do.
I have learned to read.
I'm sorry, what?
It could still be a trigger, but it trigger
a different response.
Right.
The analogy I use, I don't know why.
because you can physically rewire your brain.
You can make new new pathways and CBT
DBT.
I mean, I haven't done that before, so it's, yeah,
that's what I've been doing for decades.
The analogy I use is when I had a trigger
um, you know, I'm, I'm I'm in a car.
I'm driving down the interstate freeway, whatever you want.
I'm on the 405, okay?
I'm in I'm in LA County.
I'm driving on the 405.
Something triggers me.
I figure out what the trigger is.
I love when I lose my train of thought right in the middle of a good fucking sentence.
Going down there.
What are you just talking about.
Going down the 405, something triggers you.
Right, but before that, I need to get led back into what I was thinking, and I can't scroll in the captions.
Thank you, Zoom
So..
I think.
What were we talking about?
Is a problem?
We both do this.
I know.
We were talking about triggers.
Going on the road on the 405.
Oh, yes, my analogy.
So I have a trigger trigger triggers me in the past.
I would immediately take the exit.
That's my exit.
Here's the trigger.
Here's the trauma.
Here's my exit.
This is familiar.
This is what I'm used to.
I'm here now.
Yay
What happens now, the
ones that I have identified, I'll be driving down the 405.
Oh, oh, look, there's that exit.
Yeah, that was a fucking horrible time.
And then I just keep driving, drive right past it.
I think it is important to know for
me, I don't know if this is everybody, for me, even
after you learn the trigger, even after you have worked through it
and have created that new pathway, the trigger is still there.
Yeah.
Oh, no, the only can be there.
Right.
The memory is there.
It's always going to be there.
And, and
maybe that might be what confuses or turns people away
is when they hear, you know, oh, you'll heal.
You'll get through this and you'll just heal.
You might get better.
You might, you might, you might not.
But that memory is never going to go
away, but how you react to it is what changes.
So I'm driving down this the 405
trigger, gross.
Well, I have a new pathway in my head.
Okay, well, that happened, but it doesn't really bother me anymore because that was forever ago.
Keep driving.
Right path.
I've heard a metaphor from a couple from a YouTuber, I've really used to follow a lot
So like things in your past are like
like a scar on a tree, like if you carve your name into it or whatever.
Those things, they're not going to get smaller.
They're going to stay in about the same place
and the same size, but the tree will get bigger.
Right.
So, like, they might seem big, but
as you grow, those things are the
same size of smaller compared to your life experiences.
That's a good analogy.
Okay, so you herd a tree and you carve
your name, you carve something into it.
The tree is just going to grow straight up.
Yeah, and that thing is going to stay in roughly the same spot.
Well, I mean, it's going to grow with it, right?
Won't it move up as the tree grows?
I guess depending on the age of the tree and where you put it, sure, that place into this, I guess
But yeah, I mean, if it's an established tree,
yes, it's just going to pretty much stay where it is.
But the tree evolves and gets bigger and gets stronger,
you know, better footing, reach for that light.
And then, boom, beautiful, strong tree.
That metaphor
just really has helped me in a lot of a lot of saying it.
It's just a helpful metaphor for my mental health.
And what do you do, visualize it?
Like, does something pop in your head and you're like, oh, I need to let me
ground real quick and go, you fall back on that?
It's not really a visualized thing.
It's more, it is a grounding thing, but it's just a remembering
Just.
Be mindful.
I mean, I hate that word, but Jesus, yeah, just being mindful.
In the in the moment, in the present.
Okay, so you get manic for a week or two.
You're out on the road.
Are you worried about your nest egg and
manic draining your bank account?
I won't.
It won't be as easy for me because I won't be able to
just buy things in California and have a place to put them.
Oh, that's fair, because now that you're..
Oh, I didn't even think about that.
Things you start collecting a lot. along the way, you're going to need to drop off somewhere.
And if I' if I'm in like California or somewhere, anywhere out west,
or even anywhere on the East Coast, it's it's just not a really good deal on a Jeep.
I'll have to pass it.
Or tow it behind you and convert it as an
add-on bedroom to your RV.
I think Dell's going to need to have a word with you.
Why?
Why would she have to have a word with me?
You might be encouraging.
Is it the bad things that I do?
I mean, I guess not bad, but...
Yeah, when people have..
What?
I think it's called enabling?
Enabling, yes.
And it's, it can be dangerous when you have other friends with similar
mental health because you guys can feed off each other.
That is a thing.
And if you're ever manic and you're happy, like if I see you happy and you're like, should I buy this?
I'm going to be like, fuck yeah, you should.
It's going to make you happy.
I don't know your manic.
Yeah.
I don't even know.
And that's the thing, too.
Sometimes you don't know your manic.
Do you have anything that you know that
helps you be like, oh, fuck, a manic?
How do you know you were manic for a week or two?
Once I start looking at big purchases, I really should like a little red flag.
So it's checking the bank statement, you're like, fuck, I was manic.
Yeah.
So I've started
here lately, or at least I'm trying to,
if I am looking into something for more more than
like a month or two,
if I'm not doing that, it's probably a manic episode.
But if I've thought it out and I have all this idea, this
idea, and I've been really excited about it for
a couple months, it's likely, likely not a manic episode.
But when I see
when I see like a box truck for $2,000 and
I'm like, I have to buy this and it's in Cleveland and I buy it
and don't know how I'm going to get it home.
And don't buy it't know if I's
hot and then see the, you know, covered in rust
in an engine that knocks.
Hey, I got it.
It's still, it's sitting in London in a field because it's not worth repairing.
Can you recover any money from it?
Like sell it for parts or something?
With that one, I'm going to use
basically all the mechanical parts.
So like the gas tank with the fuel pump, the.
Oh, for your RV in case something goes on., I'm going to use all I'
to use as much of that as I can to do my engine
swap because I'm going to need a radiator.
I'm going to like a new radiator.
I'm going to need
a transmission, and the one in there is the one I want.
And it's rebuilt.
That's like the nicest thing in it.
It's it rebuilt.
Yeah, it's got like 3,500 miles on a rebuilt.
Oh, whoa.
Yeah.
And I'm going to grab the gas tank and I might use the rear axle
because it has disc brakes in the rear.
Are you going to be keeping any parts on hand in your RV when you're travelinging?
Like any common things that might go out, like a hoses, belt, something like that, that's easy to stow.
One of the reasons why I
am moving to a newer engine is and it's a very popular engine
is that I can go to any, any parts place and get get parts for it.
Oh, that's another thing to
think of. is how old the vehicle is will you be able to find parts on your route?
That's too bra.
And that, and that engine
is like the most popular
engine for hot rotting and vehicles, truck engines.
It's just a very, very popular family.
So
every, every like
parts store has the stuff I would need.
If not, then they can order it for like the next day.
Right.
Also, if you need to use tools, that's another good thing.
If you're RV, you can pull over there.
If you don't have like all your tools and you need
a breaker bar to get, you know, a nut
off something, ha, you can do that.
All right.Reilly, they won'tan them to you.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
So back to
back to living our lives around our mental health.
Aside.
I'm trying to hold it back.
Aide
from
RVing.
What, if any, other changes are you making
to better live with your mental health?
Well, I mean, just to move into a part-time job.
Well, I mean, two huge things. nomadically, lifestyle
and an RV and then, you know, job change.
Those are big things
Yeah, those are the two major things that I did,
you know, giving up on the career, realizing that, you know, what
I don't, you kind of redefine success.
Yes.
But, You're not getting,
well, well, like most people with me, I don't I don't, I wouldn't say giving up.
You just realized not.
Well, you change it.
You change your definition.
So like
most people will think, you know, making, getting
into their dream job and being successful and like financial success.
Right.
Climbing,imbing the ladder, so to speak.
That's where I wanted to go.
That's just not meant for everybody, but we're all told that from the beginning
Yep.
But, you know, some of us realize that's
it's just not the thing.
It's not it.
No, capitalism can fuck itself.
I...
What?
Eat the rich.
Feed the rich to the hungry.
Fuck you.
Feed the rich to the hungry and the poor.
No, I'm not promoting cannibalism.
A little bit.
No, no, I'm really not.
God, if
I got into politics right now, we would, this episode would be so long.
That's what he said.
How else can you change your life for your mental health?
I mean, I mean, change the place you live.
I
I don't know.
I think one thing I would that would
help because it's going to be different for everybody.
But like picture yourself
in five years if money wasn't wasn't the issue.
There was no issue without what would you be doing?
Or in five years.
What would you be doing if you weren't worried about making money,
weren't worried about climbing the ladder, weren't worried about buying a big house.
And, you know, if you're like us,
pursue that, set that as your goal.
If you're like us, meaning mental health?
Meaning that we just don't fit into the cutter.
The mold that.
Yeah.
My pictures of the van build and
then pictures of the RV build.
Talk about that.
You have two vehicles, actually.
So what is your plan for that?
The van is going to be more
of a exploration vehicle.
It's smaller.
It can fit on trails, better.
Oh, like the away shuttle from the Enterprise.
Yeah. park and then go sightsee.
But it's not going to go out on every trip with the RV.
It's just going to be like the weekender kind of thing.
And then we also have disced making
a guest room when we're on the road.
Right.
I was just going to say, if someone wanted to come join you, yeah, go run by my house.
My brother's there.
Here's the keys.
And then they get in the vehicle and they drive to you.
Yeah.
How cool is that?
And then they can just drive back, park it, and, hey, we just visited Brandon.
Oh, where'd you go?
Washington State.
That's where they're based right now.
Why?
Middle of the desert, you know, stuff like that.
Oh, I mean if it's too hot, I probably won't visit.
It gets cold at night from what I gather.
Then I guess I'll be visiting you at night.
This body doesn't do heat very well.
Doesn't like it.
Oh, I don't.
But I also hate winters, so my water is so gross.
Water?
Yeah, it's so gross.
It's like.
And I'm not even talking about tap water, like city water.
I'm not even talking about that peatry dish of piss.
I'm talking about just water in general
is gross and boring.
I mean, I know we need it.
Our bodies were like 5,000% water.
I get it.
That one's for you, Sarah.
We're a lot of water, but
can it have a flavor?
Like I mean, you can flavor.
Could it not come naturally that way?
Like I think even if it had a flavor,
we wouldn't be able to taste it.
Why?
Well, I don't have it.
We're 75% water.
We drink it all the time.
I guess. that's fair.
Well, when I'm in the cave sometimes, I like
to I like to drink some of some of the mineral water that flows to it.
I've licked the walls before in a cave.
I've licked the rock wall before just to see what it tasted like,
you know, and that's how pandemics start, right?
That's how someone randomly get some virus or bacteria that they didn't even know existed
because they wanted to lick a fucking wall in a cave.
Was you all alone?
Yeah, it was me.
It was me.
I went to carter caves and I licked it.
00:59:39,910
*ending music plays*