Hey, humans, thanks for joining my podcast.
This podcast is a place to share unedited lived experiences regarding mental health.
We'll touch on how it shows up in our lives and provide
some tips that have worked for me and others on how to manage it.
There will be strong language and definitely the
potential for disturbing and or triggering content.
Please be aware of this and mindful of
others who may be in earshot.
Most importantly, and as horribly fucking
cliche as this sounds, you really do not have to go through this alone.
And hopefully you'll see this and feel this more and more as you listen.
And hey, if this podcast isn't for you, that's fine.
There are lots of them out there.
Find one that speaks to you and helps you.
So, let's talk mental health.
And now the boiler plate and cover your ass claws
On this podcast, unless explicitly stated,
no one on this show is a medical professional in
any way, and as such, no content on
this show is intended to be, whether implied or otherwise,
to be taken as medical advice.
If you are in crisis, please call 988
or 911 or go to your nearest emergency room.
For my fellow LGBTQ Plus community, you can text start
to 678678 to
reach the amazing people over at the Trevor Project.
Or you can call them at 866-488-7386
or you can even live chat with them on
their website at chat..org.
Concertos of Chaos is sponsored by self- magnitude,
an ethical microrobusiness helping people show up as
their boldest, truest selves, at work, at play, and everywhere in between.
Founded by Maggie Green, a queer neurodivergent
brand and style strategist, self-magnitude
offers trauma-informed, affirming support for personal brand and style that reflects all of who you are
Learn more at selfagnitude.com.
And while you're there, check out Maggie's Gay It Forward initiative to support Queer Folks in Need.
Hello, everyone.
Thanks for joining me.
We didn't have an episode last week, so I wanted to talk
about that on this week's episode titled
A Pja Torres and Fermatas.
When holding onFs with Your Harmony.
Real quick, an Apatra is a musical
theory term. used to describe
a grace note ornamental, something
that's not typically part of the measure,
so to speak, can create tension resolution
It's not constrained to the timing of that measure.
And a firmata, also known as bird's
eyes, or the bird eye, means to hold that note or to hold that rest
for as long as you want.
So
Last week, I did not produce an episode.
A lot was going on.
There was still a lot going on.
And it kind of consumed me.
And I wanted to talk about the paradox of productivity.
And it's not lost on me the irony of not doing a mental
health podcast episode due to mental health.
That's not lost on me.
I want to talk about how taking breaks and
stepping back is actually a form of productivity.
A lot of people view rest
as laziness, like, we're lazy, we don't want
to do anything, but it's critical
for sustainable performance, right?
To be able to keep doing what I do or to keep doing what
you do, you have to be in the right mindset to do so.
And what happened with me is a perfect example.
I had to take time that I needed
to ensure I was at my best.
If I'm not at my best or damn
close to it, I can't give you my best.
I can't give anybody my best.
And I have to ensure my long term authenticity
of who I am, what I believe in,, this podcast's
core values, my core, which are my core values.
And this challenges that toxic
productivity narrives that society
pushes people to constantly produce
at the expense of our wellbeing.
True commitment is not about never missing a be
but more maintaining the integrity with
yourself and your audience, which is you all.
I'm being as transparent as I can about
mine, medical health or mental health and and my mental health needs, which I'm hoping is showing
well, I'm being vulnerable, which isn't something I like to do.
But it shows my vulnerability and
I guess authenticity.
I want to break down the myth that professionals, people who work
must always appear superhuman and invulnerable.
So I want to talk about today mental health
and when you need to take a break, and it's okay to take a break.
Taking breaks and and stepping back is actually a form of productivity.
A lot of people view rest as waziness, but
it's critical for sustainable performance
This podcast and last week's non-existent episode
is a perfect example of this by taking the time that I needed
to ensure my long-term
quality and authenticity of my podcast, my episodes.
And this challenges the toxic bullshit productivity narrative
that we've all been bred into us to believe
that tells us, I need to constantly produce at the expense of my health.
Grind, grind, grind.
I love you all, but you're not worth my inner harmony.
So we need to redefine commitment
and professionalism.
True commitment isn't about never missing a beat.
It's about maintaining your integrity and the integrity
of what you're doing with yourself and your audience, by
being transparent about your mental health needs, your
modeling, vulnerability, and
authenticity.
This approach completely destroys the
myth that professionals must always appear
invulnerable and superhuman.
So let's unpack that real quick.
Today's work culture
demands continuous output,
regardless, treating us like machines rather than the complex
beings that we are with the emotional and mental needs.
Choosing our needs over arbitrary
production metrics is a form of resistance
and a fuck you to capital.ism.
So is there a difference between, you know, self care
and avoidance?
Yes, there is.
And so we have the
start tiny, like microscopic tiny.
So is there a difference between strategic self care
and avoidance?
Yes, there is a difference between self care and avoidance.
Avoidance is a defense mechanism.
We attempt to escape or ignore the challenging
situations, and we suppress emotions or problems
instead of addressing them. tempporarily
alleviating discomfort without resolving underlying issues,
uh, creating short term relief at the potential cost of long term growth
using distractions or withdrawal
as a primary coping strategy.
Avoidance is like putting a Band-Aid on a broken leg.
Strategic self-care is getting some crutches,
seeing a doctor, and actually healing.
It's about facing your shit, but not in the brual way.
More like,kay, this sucks, but,
you know, I got I've got this, I can do it."
Instead of, this sucks
I'm gonna hide forever.
I'm gonna retreat.
This always happens.
The bottom always seems to fall out.
The key difference
difference is, I should say, lie in the intentionality and the long term impact.
Selfcare empowers you and helps you become more resilient.
And avoidance ultimately increases
stress and prevents personal development.
Some examples. repeatedly calling
in sick to escape work stress without addressing the root cause.
That's avoidance.
Self care, taking a mental health day
to rest, reflect, and recharge.
Refusing to look at bank statements,
ignoring bills, spending impulsively to feel better, I've been there.
Strategic selfcare, counteract that, creating a
budget, setting financial goals, learning about personal
finances, seeking financial counseling, if able, and
if needed, developing a debt repayment plan.
If that's, you know, a situation situation you're in
Consistently declining invitations,
isolating completely to prevent potential social discomfort, that's avoidance.
Gradually exposing yourself to social situations,
practicing social skills, seeking therapy, if needed,
using anxiety management techniques like deep breathing
that strategic self care..
Ignoring persistent health problems,
ignoring our bodies, avoiding medical checkups, simply out of fear.
Yes, mental health, I get it.
but that's still avoidance.
Strategic self care is kind of
forcing yourself to do regular medical checkups, tuning
in and listening to your body when it tells you something, addressing health concerns proactively
developing healthy lifestyle habits, Suppressing
emotions, using substances to numb our feelings,
and refusing to acknowledge emotional pain.
Yes, avoidance.
Self-care.
Journaling, talking with
trusted friends, again, seeking therapy if needed,
practicing emotional regulation techniques, and we will will get into some of those.
So, just a quick little bullet point here of some
indicators of strategic self care, things that are good.
Proactive approach, long term perspective,
personal growth orientation, healthy boundary setting
emotional intelligence, and problem solving focus.
The opposite, avoidance, is a reactive approach.
It's a short term relief, temporary escape
and it increases anxietyiety over time.
You have emotional suppression, and problem
perpetuating behavior.
It's a cycle that we need to
break.
So we need to redefine what commitment
is and what professionalism is.
So true commitment is not about never missing a beat.
We're human.
We can't do that.
It's about maintaining your integrity with yourself and
your audience, whoever that may be, whether it be a podcast,
audience, radio, audience, TV, audience, or friends, family, whatever.
By being transparent about your mental health needs
you' modeling vulnerability and authenticity.
And that approach completely destroys
the myth that we must always appear invulnerable
and superhuman.
So let's unpack this real quick.
Today's work culture demands, pretty
much all demands, continuous output.
regardless of the expense.
Treating us like machines rather than complex beings with
emotional and mental needs.
Choosing our needs over arbitrary productivity
metrics is a form of resistance and a fuck you to capitalism.
So if you're feeling overwhelmed, just take three deep breaths.
If you can't face that whole messy room,
just clean one surface, one table, one little nightstand,
show some progress to yourself.
Stressed out about work.
Send that one email that you have been avoiding and get it
off your plate, if you can.
Practice saying no.
I know we've discussed this before because no is a full sentence.
So a friend wants to hang out when you're exhausted.
Sorry, can't today.
You get extra work dumped on you at work.
I can't take that on right now.
Family drama invitation.
Not today, Satan.
But not this.
Hey, there's a fire in the kitchen.
Hand me that extinguisher.
No, I don't do red things."
Wayne, but avoidance.
When you can do emotional triage,
you will better understand what's happening in your brain.
So think of your mental health like a first aid kit.
If you're feeling low, ask yourself,
what's the smallest thing that might help me feel even 1% better?
Could be drinking some water, stepping outside, petting a
dog, listening to one good song?
That's all it takes.
And then boundaries.
Boundaries, they're not walls.
They're guardrails.
Work is trying to own your wife, right?
No, set an end of work alarm.
I used to do this, and an office maid of mine used to do this.
We would set our alarms on our phones for about
five to 10 minutes before work was over so
that we could start wrapping things up and firing off
emails that need to be finished, you know, shutting down some equipment,
things like that.
Instead of waiting to the last minute, when 5 o'clock
hits, and then you have to do all this stuff that you're
not being paid to do past five o'clock.
You've got a toxic friend always dumping on you.
Well, you limit the call times, but maybe
also look inwards as to why you still have a toxic friend.
That could be a problem.
Family pushing your buttons, and you have to
go to this event, well, have a preplanned exit strategy.
Have someone call you 15 minutes in as
a kind of test the waters to see how things are and how you're feeling
And if you already know, it's going to be a shit show,
then tell your friend to call you back in whatever time span you need,
five minutes, 30 minutes an hour, and leave.
Nothing wrong with that.
Remember, know always a full sentenceence, and you owe
no one an excuse as to why you cannot do something.
Now, we've been raised
that we require an excuse on when you ask someone, "Hey, can you do this?
Can you meet me?
Can you.
No, I can't."
Oh, how come
you don't need to know how come.
I just cannot do it.
It's powerful when you accept that, that you just say no, and that's that.
You, at least I did, get a little uncomfortable when
I would get pushed back on that, and I don't get uncomfortable anymore.
I mean, Noah's no.
You don't you don't need to know what's going on in my life, know is no.
And then you want to create what I call
the fuck it bucket list.
Create a list of
no pressure activities that might make you feel good.
A 10 minute walk.
Doodling, arts, crafts, paintings, slowly tearing sheets of paper.
Fuck, what a relaxing sensation it
is to tear sheets of paper.
I don't waste paper, though.
I use the already wasted resources of the 5 billion
unsolicited paper shit I get in my mailbox daily.
Maybe we should start boxing that up and shipping it back to the post office.
I wonder if we all did that, if it would stop.
Call a friend who actually gets you.
Dance in your kitchen..
Watch a lame ass comedy movie, all things that can pull you out
if you're feeling crappy.
Another good thing is
is to catch the negative thought pattern.
So when your brain is starting to doom spiral,
if you can recognize that spiral and then
change what you tell yourself about the spiral.
Not, fuck, I'm spiraling.
Here we go.
It's done, the day has ruined..
I'm struggling right now, and that's okay.
I will use the tools in my resource box and
maybe call a friend or two who gets me and can talk me down and help me through this.
You need to think of your energy like a
currency, sadly, in a bank.
Some things we do or done to us
deposit energy into our bank.
And then some things that we do and that are done
to us withdraw money. from that bank.
Toxic people
doom scrolling, overworking,
excessively putting needs before
your own at the expense of your
health, push, push, push, push, grind, grind, grind, side hustle, going,
going, going, until you enter burnout.
Burnout's not fun.
Make a list, try to track the things that
fill you up versus drain you.
You cannot pour from an empty cup.
It's not about being perfect.
It's about being slightly less shitty to yourself.
We need to be nicer to ourselves.
Some days, strategic self care might just mean you survived the fucking day.
And you know what?
That counts.
That's a Gold Star sticker on the board.
I think we negate that for
some people just surviving the day,
took up every resource they had.
So, how do people,
whether content creators, whatever we are, balance
consistency with our personal wellbeing.
What things or responsibilities do we owe
to our audiences or whomever versus what we owe to ourselves?
I owe you me.
That's it.
I owe you my authentic self.
And I cannot be anything other than me.
And when I'm not at my best, I cannot provide
you or anyone, me, or my best.
Is Wes than best okay?
Fuck, yes, it is.Cause we can't always be our best 247 365.
We're human, it's not possible.
You will get burnt out.
Physical fatigue
or mental blurs, which are painful.
We simply can't do it.
What if taking care of yourself is your most important work?
And how can we create environment that normalize
mental health breaks?
You are more than the sum of your output.
We all are.
One way way to kind
of tackle this is to
recognize the symbol or symbols, recognize the signals
in your body with five simple questions.
I hate the phrase to be present,
but being present in your body kind of is what we need to
combat mental health.
You can keep a log or a journal if you need to, or an app.
Everything's an app now, and kind of track your
not triggers, but yellow flags
on the field, if you will, kind of an early alerting system to
help keep track and point out when you might need to take a pause
by doing a self-check in.
If you're feeling away and or
are unsure why you're feeling that way, or maybe you don't even know what you're feeling
I've been there, it's kind of a bitch.
But try this.
Try it.
You never know.
It works for me.
Try it.
Five questions.
Have I eaten?
Have I had any water in the past two to three hours?
Do I have to use the bathroom when I've been holding it all this time?
Am I tired?
Does my body hurt?
Five simple questions, right?
Okay, let's dive in.
So, have I eaten?
Everyone heard hangry?
Oh, this person's hangry because they haven't eaten.
Well, let's talk about why.
Your brain consumes about 20
to 25, maybe percent of your body's energy.
So you need to constantly fuel it, provide your brain fuel.
Your blood sugar
affects your cognitive functioning.
Low blood sugar can trigger the stress hom
the stress hormone, our good old friend cortisol,
which can cause reduced attention span, increased irritability
and decreased self-control.
So your attention span shit.
You are heightened, irritable, and you have less self control.
What do you think is going to happen?
Number two, have I had any water without the past two to three hours?
Now, as I told Sarah in the last episode, you know,
your bodies are 50,000% water, so
what do we need to do here?
2% dehydration, just 2% dehydration
causes. 10
to 15% cognitive performance decline.
Your short- term memory kind of becomes shit
More cortisol, baby, is squirted into the body.
Your neural processing slows, you know, that thing that we really need to function.
And your concentration is reduced.
The brain, about 73% water,
dehydration increases neural energy expenditure.
That means your brain is doing more with West than it needs to.
A lack of water reduces your brain's ability to
sustain optimal electrical firing.
Food and water are important.
The third one, do I have to use the bathroom?
Mm.
Okay.
So physical discomfort increases your cognitive load.
More shits on your plate now.
Bladder tension activates a stress response.
And what does that do?
Cortesol!
It reduces your working memory capacity
and increases distraction and anxiety.
It can trigger a quite popular response that I work learned not too recently
or not too long ago, all courtesy
of our sympathetic nervous system, fight or flight.
Stress and anxiety, you know, the two main requirements for the
brain to make the cocktail of doom that I call it, and activate fight or flight.
What's that do?
It increases your heart rate, it increases your brain breathing rate, it increases
your blood pressure, it narrows your blood vessels.
It improves your eyesight and slows digestion.
I assume those are for the either fighting or flighting.
I guess it'd be either.
I'm not sure.
And it's activated when you're stressed in danger, or just physically active
It's now for some nerd.
It originates in your thoracic and oneumbar
regions of your spinal c cord, and it uses nor epinephrine
to act on the targeted issues, or targeted tissues, sorry.
It's one of two divisions of the autonomic
nervous system, along with the parasympathetic nervous system.
B. This system, the sympathetic,
responds to changes in caloric intake.
Okay?
So you've not eaten.
So, example
you have a caloric restriction that decreases
the sympathetic nervous system activity, while carbs increases it.
And for all of you fellasellow coffee lovers, caffeine
can also stimulate the sympathetic nervous system.
Four am I tired?
Sweep deprivation, mimics alcohol impairment.
Many studies here, 17 to 19
hours consistently being awake
is the equivalent of 0.05%
blood alcohol content, BAC.
And what's that do?
Well, it reduces emotional regulation, which then
increases emotional reactivity.
It reduces your complex problem solving,
your reaction time, your decision making accuracy,
and it increases impulsive behavior.
So one, two, three, and four are all kind of playing along with
each other here, really, really, really fucking you.
Then we come down to number five, does my body hurt?
You should track the patterns in your energy,
your mood, and your give a fucks bucket capacity.
Create a personal dashboard of your mental health indicators
in your mind if possible, or you can make a physical one.
We can talk about that later.
Chronic pain
Activates your brain's threat detection system.
It knows there's a problem, which now increases your
cognitive load again due to your brain focusing on
trying to determineermine the source, the cause?
Is it bad?
Is it temporary?
Do I need to stop what I'm doing?
Do I need to go to the hospital, et cetera.
It reduces your prefrontal cortex functionality,
and that controls executive functioning, working memory
regulating, and changing behavior,
decision making, balancing rewards, and goals,
meaning a instant gratification versus a long-term
goal, predicting consequences and focusing attention.
It also triggers
our longtime friend again, cortisol, that awesome stress hormone.
And what does that affect?
Attention, working memory, and emotional processing.
So those five things that seem kind
of small can truly affect your mood.
Have I eaten?
Have I had any water in the past two to three hours?
Do I have to use the bathroom and been holding it?
Am I tired?
And does my body hurt?
So what do we do with this?
Well, I did something that I
learned in therapy
and it's to build a toolk kit.
And it's not, it doesn't have to be tangible.
It doesn't have to be something physical you carry around.
It does help, but it doesn't have to be.
And you just need to develop three to five minute little things.
Five of them at least.
That way it's a 15 minute type of deal.
To kind of help you reboot, reset, reign
with yourself, realign with what you know is true to you.
One of them, I'm sure you've heard is a sensory grounding techniques.
People use different things, things in their pocket.
For me, I have a necklace
that you can't see around my neck that I use
It's a, well, here, I'll just pull it out.
You may not be able to see it.
It's a little green heart
locket type of deal. and it's got some
of my grand grandma's ashes in it.
So wherever you are, if possible, look
around, find some things you can focus on for a minute or two, like a
lamp, a stain on the wall, a pencil, that's under your a table, a parked car, a dog shitting on your walln.
It doesn't matter what it is
Just focus on it and then describe
it out loud.
Describe some features of it,
and if you can, touch it.
But not the dog example.
Don't touch that.
Concrete tangible things, something you can physically
connect with, seems to work much, much, much better than non tangible things.
and words have power, especially when counteracting
mental health and talking to yourself.
I'm not sure why saying stuff out loud
sticks more than if I just try to remember it
or write it down somewhere and then never going back and looking at it again.
Meditation with scheduled
mini breaks is another amazing thing to have in your toolbox.
You don't have to meditate for 15, 20, 30 minutes a day.
You don't have to own and do you don't have to do that
It can be anything that
clears your mind and has no
distractions to allow you to just
E. Just B. It could be in a room with some music.
It could be in a room with no music, some incense,
a favorite blanket, a favorite food, a flower, a lamp, whatever you need to center
do it.
And then two more really important ones
for this toolk kit is get the fuck up and move brakes.
You need to get up and move.
I don't, and I need to do this more.
When you sit or away
all the time, all the time.
Your body hates you.
Your circulatory system hates you.
You're not at the prime circulation that you really should be having.
We need to walk and move and stretch
minimum, 10, 15 minutes a day, I'd say, three times a day.
And it doesn't have to be some sweat your ass
off exertion, you know, heat stroke type of deal.
Just
walk the perimeter of the inside of your apartment.
I've done that.
Walk back and forth and pace.
Go outside and walk around your house or your apartment or whatever.
Just get up and move.
Or
sit on the floor and do some stretching.
All of that releases the endorphins that help make you feel better or can help make you feel better.
And the last one is the boundary setting scripts.
People have can have some issues
setting boundaries, but more importantly,
they have a lot of issues coming up with what the boundary should
be, not so much setting it and enacting it or enforcing it, I should say.
So it'd be good to come up with a few short little things
remind you that you have
boundaries yourself.
You have boundaries with yourself.
So have some of those little boundaries in
your little toolk kit and remind yourself, hey,
Christopher, you set up this boundary.
Yeah, I know, but no, you set this up.
because you don't want this to happen again
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, you're right.
Okay, I need to do that.
So they're not necessarily scripts for setting boundariesaries with other people.
They're the ones that you have set with yourself
to help stay aligned with who you are.
Just reminders, we're human.
We're gonna fall, we're gonna fail, or a happy mistake.
Sorry, it's not a fail or a happy accident.
Because it can always be
spun a different way.
Well, spun a different way, meaning not how the media does.
Whatever else you need to add to your toolk kit, you can.
Absolutely.
And something else that will really, really
help is to reframe what productivity is.
No matter what you do, what your task is, you
don't want to put everything on
the quantitative, right?
Quantity.
How much did I do?
How much did I put out this day?
How
Don't.
That's not a measure of how good you are.
It's not the quantity.
It's the qualitative, the quality.
Did you put out a whole bunch bunch great, but it's all shit?
Or were you able to put out one thing
and it's great?
Where's the balance?
It's. best if you
can do one thing that's good versus
10 to 15 things that are counterproductive and not good.
So if you can reframe it in your
mind to, it's not about how much I do, it's
about how well I'm doing.
And that helps you challenge the internalized capitalistic bullshit myths that have been bred into us.
And recognizing rest as active recovery
not a weakness.
Rest is not a weakness.
Create an accountability
with a comparison, so to speak.
So find one to two people or three,
whoever, who really understand your mental health, the journey you're on, and how
people should treat and respond to you so so
that you can give them your best.
And we actually talked about this an episode or
two ago with my guest, Brandon.
I think, or C season two, or maybe three, I'm not sure.
You need to build support systems that validate
you, that validate your needs, that validate who you are.
You need that.
If you don't have that,
you're not going to be happy.
You need people in your life who get you.
And they don't like Eor,
somewhat of an okay example, Eor and Winnie the Pooh, right?
Chronically depressed, chronically sad and down.
and all of his friends know this, but they're still his friends.
They don't judge him for it.
And they don't try to change him for it.
They.
They don't try to change Eor.
They don't try to make fun of Eor.
It's just
That's our friend Eor.
Mental health, he's sad, depressed, pretty much most of the time.
But we love them.
We love Eor, and we're gonna stick with Eor.
Those friends are key.
Finding people like that are key key
Very, very, very key.
So we have some adaptive strategies.
Lovely word, to kind of help fight
this grind, grind, grind, burnout culture.
Build a flexible
plan, contingency plan, if you will,
for your job, if you have a job,
your personal life, creative projects, whatever you're doing.
Allow yourself to mess up.
Allow yourself to make a mess.
Someone told me that. the other day when I
was in a not great place and dealing
with art, 'cause I'm trying to paint more,
and it just enages me because it's not what I see in my head on
the canvas.
And it enrages me.
And then I was told, allow yourself to make a mess.
You're still learning.
Allow yourself to mess it up.
And I think
it enrages and bothers me so much is because
two things.
One, it's not really the artistic outlet.
That's me.
It's not my choice.
It's It's fun, but that's not my choice.
And that's one reason.
And the second reason is because
I'm not excelling at it as quickly as I did with piano.
And the two of those reasons combined
really cost them spiraling in my head.
Like, for instanceance, when I finished the one over here, I threw it on the floor.
I just didn't give a fuck, because it just doesn't
look like what I had in my head.
But as I sit here right now and I'm looking over at it, and different
lighting at a different angle, it doesn't look bad.
It really doesn't.
But it's not what I wanted.
But it's not bad.
So, I don't always get what we want, but it doesn't necessarily mean it's going to be bad
either.
So create some buffer zones, create breaks,
and whatever you do so that you can quickly regroup, set
an alarm on your phone for every so many, whatever, an hour, two hours
and do it.
Don't, oh, I don't feel like I need one right now.
Do it.
Every time you put, I don't feel like I need it.
I don't feel, oh, I can go a little longer.
I can go a little longer.
You're gonna crash.
You're gonna burn out.
It happens.
Listen to your body.
It doesn't lie.
Practice communicating changes proactively
with people, even if
looking in the mirror and starting with yourself.
And I actually recommend you do start with yourself.
It was cheesy as hell when I tried it, I'm not going to lie.
And it did kind of make me think of that Bloody Mary thing looking in the mirror growing up.
But anyhow, I digress.
Start with your yourself.
If there are changes you want to make and say
you have a list, and it's kind of a daunting list,
pick one or two things, maybe
even just one, and tell yourself about it.
Have a conversation with yourself.
It's okay.
It's the one person you can talk to, that you kind of know how they're going to respond.
So it's okay.
Talk to yourself.
If you want to look in the mirror, do it, if you want to look into your phone, do it,
just have a conversation with yourself.
And I don't mean internally in your head.
I mean out loud.
Why?
There is something to talking out
loud that makes it stick.
Something like writing when we used to have to write things 50% ofajillion times, you remembered it.
I don't mean like writing sentences when you got in trouble, because.
Anyway, I just mean writing things down like in school, taking notes and stuff.
I did retain it longer if I wrote it down
versus putting it in my head, which is just a
shit mess trying to remember things and organize.
But writing it down made it stick.
Something else you can do is I don't have one.
I need to build it back up, an emergency mental health fund so
that you can treat yourself whenever you need.
I'm not saying retail therapy.
I'm just saying if you're having an exceptionally
bad time or something and you have some, you know,
mental health fundage,, get something,
whatever it is, get something that will help you
And I'm not here to tell you what you should
or should not get with your mental health fund.
That's up to you.
Only you know what's going to help you.
You also want to negotiate,
well, this shit's all over the place, negotiate flexible working arrangements,
and explore, you know, resources that are available to you
at your job if you are working.
Another big thing is changing how
you see yourself, changing how you think about mental health
the stigma, the stereotypes,
the words people use when talking about mental health.
your worth is not the sum of your output.
What you can do is not who you are.
What you can do
is not what makes you your give you value and your worth.
You're more than that.
Sustainability trumps intensity.
Vulnerability is a superpower.
It is not a weakness.
It's scary as thought to be vulnerable
Not going to lie, I will agree with everyone who just screamed yes on that.
But it's not a weakness.
It's not.
You can't really grow
if you're not vulnerable and take that chance.
You can't.
So all of this said.
Write down some sentences, maybe, or you can type them up.
That's fine if you wanted to type them up on your computer.
and you can start it with I am more, whatever.
I am more than
whatever.
And make sure it's things that have to do with your life.
You know, I am more than a pretty little butterfly.
It's cute, yes, we get it.
But
you're not physically a butterfly.
So try to make these something about you in
your life to help you reinforce, and you
want to say these out loud, to help you reinforce
you.
Help you reinforce you, your
strengths, who you are, who you want to be, where you want to go.
I went ahead and made a whist more than I thought, and you don't have to make this many.
But I did.
I did.
I'm going to share it with you.
But I'm actually going to change it from I am to
UR. for the ones that are kind of like a blanket statement that go to everybody.
And then I'll change them back to I am for the ones that specifically pertain to my life
which most are I am.
Okay, so here's some.
And remember, you want to say these out loud.
You are more than the stories that people have said about you.
You are more than the labels that people tried
to define and swap on you.
You are more than the skills that provided you income.
You are more than the challenges that made you.
100% of the shit that life throughout you, you survived.
You're still here.
I am more than the classical pianist who lost the majority of his hearing.
I am more than the person who had perfect pitch and
tuned your instrument when no other resources were available to do so.
I am more than an IT genius who
can make technology bend at my will.
I am more than the traumas that said,
you're not enough and you're not going to be enough enough.
I am the symphony of my own resilience.
I am the code that rewrites its own algorithm that refuses to be predictable and fit in.
I am am the glitch in your perfect fucked up system.
We are the static between your neat little categories.
We are the scream that you try to silence.
We are the noise that refuses to be silenced.
I am the trauma that gave me my goddamn voice.
We try, we fail.
We rupture, we break.
We try.
We fail..
We break through.
We rebuild.
We try.
I am human.
I am mental health.
We are human, and
we are mental health.
Pick whatever sentences that
resonate with you, things that people may have told you
opposite of what you know to be true, use those if you need to.
Make as many as you need and read them to yourself.
Out loud in front of a mirror,
if you can.
It can seem a little hokey at first, so maybe just start reading them out loud.
Or, you know what?
Hey, even just start reading them to yourself quietly.
Start there.
Eventually, you'll see you're going to start saying them out loud.
Like, something's going to happen during the day and you're going to be like, oh, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
I am the symphony of my own resilience, not you.
And then you'll start saying them and saying them, and then
they become second nature, and then you have weapons,
you have mental health weapons to combat
bullshit that I like to call wife.
So, that's really all I had today.
to let people know you do not have to
grind, you can take time for your mental health.
You cannot be your best if you're not at your best.
And even if you're not at your all best, you can still give
not your all best, and it still be enough.
That's okay.
Just take the time to do what
you need to do to be the better you
and fuck everybody else.
They're not you.
They're not living your life.
They're not walking in your shoes.
They're not putting up with your family.
They're not putting up with your friends
They're not putting up with your medical issues.
So why are we going to aot them some of our energy?
You, have the conversation with yourself.
And I think you're going to be pleasantly
surprised if you can follow through with it and do it.
So feel free to send questions,
comments about any of the topics that
I've discussed or we've discussed on the show.
And if they're appropriate for the podcast and
with your permission, we'll go ahead and discuss them.
And when I say appropriate
you know, there's always someone who's going to send in something that, no,
so I hate hate having to vet shit like
that, but, you know, this is the world we live in.
So thanks for joining me.
And we'll see you next week.
Hopefully.
On another awesome episode
of Concertos of Chaos